<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The constant maid: or, Love will finde out the way A comedy. By J.S. As it is now acted at the new playhouse called the Nursery, in Hatton-Garden.</title>
            <title>Constant maid</title>
            <author>Shirley, James, 1596-1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1667</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 153 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59976</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3462</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R219624</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831080</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831080</idno>
            <idno type="VID">35542</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A59976)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 35542)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2112:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The constant maid: or, Love will finde out the way A comedy. By J.S. As it is now acted at the new playhouse called the Nursery, in Hatton-Garden.</title>
                  <title>Constant maid</title>
                  <author>Shirley, James, 1596-1666.</author>
                  <author>T. B.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 61, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Ja: Cottrel, for Samuel Speed, at the signe of the Rainbow between the two Temple-gates,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1667.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>J.S. = James Shirley.</note>
                  <note>"The first edition, 1640, was entitled 'The constant maid' and had Shirley's name on the title.. Such variations as appear in this text, together with the epilogue may be laid to the account of 'T.B.'[who has signed the epilogue]"--Pforzheimer Catalogue.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>A reissue, with a cancel title page, of "Love will finde out the way", published in 1661.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Worcester College Library, Oxford.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:35542:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:35542:1"/>
            <p>THE Conſtant Maid: OR, <hi>Love will finde out the Way.</hi> A COMEDY.</p>
            <p>By <hi>J. Shirley</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As it is now Acted at the new Play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe called <hi>The Nurſery,</hi> in HATTON-GARDEN.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>Ja: Cotterel,</hi> for <hi>Samuel Speed,</hi> at the ſigne of the Rainbow between the two Temple-gates. 1667.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dramatis_personae">
            <pb facs="tcp:35542:2"/>
            <head>ACTORS Names.</head>
            <list>
               <item>HArtwel, <hi>a decayed Gentleman, lover of Mrs Frances.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Playfayre, <hi>Hartwel's kinſman and friend, lover of Hornet's neece.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Lambert, <hi>another of Hartwel's friends, counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit King.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Three or four counterfeit Lords of Poland.</item>
               <item>Poldavis, <hi>Master of the Horſe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Hornet, <hi>a great <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurer, ſuitor to Mrs Belamie.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Doctor of Phyſick to Hornets Neece.</item>
               <item>Startup, <hi>a Clowniſh Gentleman, Hartwel's rival to Mrs Frances.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Another Country-Gentleman, <hi>his neighbour.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Cloſe, <hi>an old truſty ſervant to Hartwel.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Three more ſervants caſhier'd.</item>
               <item>Juſtice of Peace.</item>
               <item>Purſuivant. Officers.</item>
               <item>Conſtable and Watch.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>WOMEN.</head>
               <item>Mrs Belamie, <hi>a rich Widow.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mrs Frances, <hi>her daughter, Hartwel's Miſtreſs.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Hornet's Neece, <hi>Playfayres Miſtreſs.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Nurſe.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="play">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:35542:2"/>
            <head>LOVE will finde out the Way.</head>
            <div n="1" type="act">
               <head>Actus Primus.</head>
               <stage>Enter Hartwel and Servants.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>NAy let's not part ſo heavilie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>For my own part, it does not trouble me ſo much,</p>
                  <p>That you have broke up houſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 Ser.</speaker>
                  <p>And yet that ſticks in my ſtomack:</p>
                  <p>For hoſpitality went out of faſhion, with crop-doublets and cod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieces.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>But I have worne out ſo many liveries, under your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhpful father.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>My father had an office which brought in</p>
                  <p>A fair Revenew; I inherit but</p>
                  <p>His little land, whoſe annual profits will not</p>
                  <p>Encourage me to live at the ſame hight:</p>
                  <p>You may meet better fortunes; there's enough</p>
                  <p>Preferment in the world: my love and beſt</p>
                  <p>Aſſiſtance promiſe to your ſelves.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>I do not ſtand upon wages, ſir, I wont leave you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>Not leave me? how wilt thou live?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Live? as other mortals do: yet I wont play th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thief, that's a courſe may be taken, by which a man may aſcend the ladder of preferment; but I never lov'd to climb trees: I muſt confeſs I cannot cheat; I have heard there's a deviliſh deal of knowledge in the dice, and if men wont lend mony, they'll fetch it out o'th' bones: but it's beſt caſting in a Tavern, when the reckoning and the wine come up together. Some men have
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:35542:3"/> a trick to ſpin out a living by't: there be many ſecret ways for Servingmen to live: alas 'tis not wages that does maintain all our tribe; eſpecially thoſe that have Miſtreſſes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>But I am a batchelour.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>I pray let me be one of your buttons ſtill then; I am not half worne out; ye know what mould I am made of: I e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver did you honeſt ſervice: and though the reſt of my fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vermine can leave your falling houſe, I do not fear the rafters: By this hand I will wait upon you, though as ſome gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at mens ſervants, I live upon nothing but the air of commendation</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, ſince y'are ſo reſolute, ſtill attend me; the reſt I here diſcharge: there's ſomewhat more, not worth the Name of bounty; I will all</p>
                  <p>A happier entertainment.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 Ser.</speaker>
                  <p>Heaven bleſs you, ſir, and there be no remedy.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 Ser.</speaker>
                  <p>Farewell <hi>Cloſe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Pray give me leave to wet my lips with my old fellows; ſorrow makes a dry proverb; I muſt to a Tavern, and condole a quart with 'em.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>Meet me at Miſtreſs <hi>Bellamy</hi>'s.—</p>
                  <stage>Exit Hart.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſhall, ſir.</p>
                  <stage>Enter Playfaire.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>How now, my Maſters?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>You do not ſpeak to me, ſir? I am a ſervant ſtill: in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, the caſe is alter'd with them; they are Maſters for want of a ſervice.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 Ser.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh Maſter <hi>Playfaire!</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 Ser.</speaker>
                  <p>It is not now as when <hi>Andrea</hi> liv'd.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>3 Ser.</speaker>
                  <p>This place was made for pleaſure, not for dearth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 Ser.</speaker>
                  <p>There was a time, when Mortals whetted knives. <hi>Play.</hi> What's the matter?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 Ser.</speaker>
                  <p>In time of yore, when men kill'd brutiſh beaſts.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>3 Ser.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh cruel butcher, whoſoere thou wert!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Do you not know what all this ſignifies?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play</speaker>
                  <p>Not I.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe,</speaker>
                  <p>My Maſter has given over houſe-keeping.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 Ser.</speaker>
                  <p>Burglary, ſir, burglary; our young Maſter has broke up the Celler, and thrown the Kitchen out of the Hall-window.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, he has thrown the houſe out at window; it has a ſuperſcription already; and is directed to his next loving friend, that will pay the rent. You'll hardly know me, I have no fellow.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:35542:3"/>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>Y'are very merry.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>He has caſheer'd a company.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>3 Ser.</speaker>
                  <p>And taken our good names from us.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>I know his nature is more noble; thou wort his groom.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>3 Ser.</speaker>
                  <p>Right, and now I am turn'd off, that good name is taken away; nay I am not company for his horſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Graſs and Hay, we are all mortal.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 Ser.</speaker>
                  <p>VVe may ſee what it is to be prick'd with provender; now we muſt bite o'th' bridle for't; all diſcharg'd.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>Certain?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, certain of us are; for my Maſter only belongs to me: if you would ſpeak with him, you may overtake him, he's gone to Miſtreſs <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>llamies:</hi> in the mean time I give you to underſtand, that I <hi>Cloſe</hi> do ſtill follow my Maſter; have great hope to continue eating, though the reſt of my fellows here be blanks, and want filling.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>My Maſters, I have known you long; and though you be at loſs, in the confidence of your future honeſties, I will employ yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in a device, which if it prove happy, mayreward you hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>And me too?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>No, ſir, you are another mans ſervant; follow you your Maſter: if there be occaſion, I'll enquire for you: will you be faithful to a project of mine?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                  <p>Doubt it not, ſweet Maſter <hi>Playfair,</hi> any thing.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>Follow me for your inſtructions: Farewel <hi>Cloſe,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend me to your Maſter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 Ser.</speaker>
                  <p>'Buy <hi>Cloſe,</hi> honeſt <hi>Cloſe,</hi> we are blanks.—</p>
                  <stage>Ex. Playfaire and Servant.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Roul your ſelves up, and be drawn at the next lotterie: I wont leave my certainty, for all your projects, take my word for't; if your project fail, I ſhall find ſome of you in <hi>Pauls,</hi> watching behind a pillar, with a prayer that ſome gentleman will read the bedrol, and take pitty of a very ſerviceable fellow, to wait on him; but wants a cloak, Much good do ye with your Project.—</p>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Hornet and Miſtreſs Bellamy.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Come widow, be rul'd by me; I know the world,</p>
                  <p>And I have ſtudied it theſe fifty years:</p>
                  <p>There's no man to be truſted.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>Without good</p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:35542:4"/>
                  <p>Security, you mean.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>No young man, widow,</p>
                  <p>That talks and ſays he loves you, writes you verſes,</p>
                  <p>And ſwears he ſhall go hang himſelf unleſs</p>
                  <p>You pitty him: take me an old man.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>Take you an old man: ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Seaſon'd with care and thrift, not led away</p>
                  <p>By vitious converſations, nor corrupted</p>
                  <p>With pride and ſurfeit: one that knows the uſe</p>
                  <p>Of money? d'ye mark? the uſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, ſir; uſe upon uſe, you mean.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>And dares not ſpend it prodigally; knowing</p>
                  <p>The principal end it was ordain'd to was,</p>
                  <p>To relieve neceſſity, and lay up</p>
                  <p>VVhat is above.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>To help the poor.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>You may,</p>
                  <p>If you be ſo diſpos'd; but 'tis as commendable</p>
                  <p>To give it in our will, to build an hoſpital,</p>
                  <p>And ſo our charity comes all together.</p>
                  <p>Beſides, who knows what tempeſts while we live</p>
                  <p>May riſe? 'tis wiſdom not to be without</p>
                  <p>A ſun-ſhine in our bags to quiet all:</p>
                  <p>I know you want no ſuitors in the City,</p>
                  <p>There be courtiers, great ones, with large titles,</p>
                  <p>Cold in their own eſtates, would warm themſelves</p>
                  <p>At your rich City-bonefire: there's no Alderman</p>
                  <p>Or wealthy Merchant, leaves his widow wealthy,</p>
                  <p>But ſtreight ſome noble blood, or luſtie kindred,</p>
                  <p>Claps in with his guilt coach and Flandrian Trotters,</p>
                  <p>And hurr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es her away to the next Counteſs:</p>
                  <p>No matter for corruption of their blood;</p>
                  <p>Some undone courtier made her husband rich,</p>
                  <p>And this new Lord receives it back again.</p>
                  <p>I would not have your ſtate thus eaten up</p>
                  <p>By caterpillers, but preſerv'd and made</p>
                  <p>Greater by marrying a diſcreet old man.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>And ſuch a one you ſhew your ſelf.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>You happily interpret me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>I will not tell you till we meet again,</p>
                  <p>What operation your good counſel has upon me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>She inclines; 'tis your good nature.</p>
                  <p>I'm plain <hi>Hornet,</hi> and have no tricks; I'll tell you all</p>
                  <p>My fault, I'm given much to gather wealth;</p>
                  <p>No kindred, only a neece, left to my truſt</p>
                  <p>With a great portion; one that is never like to marry.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:35542:4"/>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>Why?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>She never thriv'd ſince ſhe came to me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>I eaſily believe it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Melancholy</p>
                  <p>VVill kill her, and yet I purſue all ways</p>
                  <p>That promiſe her delight; I ſpare no coſt</p>
                  <p>Of phyſick; what her Doctor ſays, is done.</p>
                  <stage>Enter Hartwel and Frances.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis lovingly perform'd.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>VVhat's he?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>A Gentleman that bears my daughter much affection.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Sure I have ſeen him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>Maſter <hi>Hartwel.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh he's a begger, or muſt be very ſhortly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>Have you his lands in morgage?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Not yet, not yet, but he'll want money too:</p>
                  <p>His kinſman <hi>Playfair</hi> keeps him company;</p>
                  <p>Take heed on him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>He has good breeding.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Hang breeding, 'tis unluckie:</p>
                  <p>They never keep their ſtate that have too much on't:</p>
                  <p>Counſel your daughter, Miſtreſs <hi>Bellamy,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To throw him off.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>You direct well.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>VVhen we are married, I'll provide a match</p>
                  <p>For her.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>You have care on us.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>It will become me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>Is a ſuiter to thy mother.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>He would be ſuch a thing, were I not happy</p>
                  <p>In ſuch a jolly father in law.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>A looks like ſome caſt money-bag, that had given up</p>
                  <p>The ſtuffing, and for want of uſe grown mouldy:</p>
                  <p>He dares not keep a fire in's Kitchen, leſt</p>
                  <p>VVarming his hands, which rather look like gloves ſo tan'd,</p>
                  <p>And thin, he lets 'em ſcorch, and gather into a heap.</p>
                  <p>I do not think he ever put off his clothes:</p>
                  <p>He would run mad at ſight of's own anatomie.</p>
                  <p>That ſuch a wretch ſhould have ſo vaſt a wealth!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>I'll not be his Neece,</p>
                  <p>For all his fortune.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>I preſume</p>
                  <p>Your mother is more noble, then to encourage</p>
                  <p>Him in his courtſhip: her eſtate would mix</p>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:35542:5"/>
                  <p>Not well with his ill-gotten wealth, extorted</p>
                  <p>From widows and from orphans: not will all</p>
                  <p>His plenty keep his ſoul one day from famine:</p>
                  <p>'Tis time ill ſpent, to mention him; let's talk</p>
                  <p>Of ſomething elſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>Of what?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>Of love again,</p>
                  <p>Whoſe flames we equally divide.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Your table</p>
                  <p>Is a devourer, and they ſhut up doors</p>
                  <p>Firſt, that keep open houſe and entertainments:</p>
                  <p>This Lord is feaſted, and that young Ladies ſweet tooth</p>
                  <p>Muſt have a banquet: t'other old</p>
                  <p>Madam with ne'er a tooth, muſt have ſome marchpane</p>
                  <p>Coral to rub her gums withal: theſe are</p>
                  <p>Vain and ridiculous expences.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis not too late to thrive.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>This room has too rich furniture, and worſe</p>
                  <p>Hangings would ſerve the turn; if I may be</p>
                  <p>Worthy to counſel, pictures are too</p>
                  <p>Superfluous, of this and t'other maſters</p>
                  <p>Doing: hang <hi>Michael Angelo</hi> and his oyls;</p>
                  <p>If they be given, y'are the more excus'd</p>
                  <p>To let 'em hang; but have a care you let not</p>
                  <p>Appear either in Arras or in Picture,</p>
                  <p>The ſtorie of the prodigal, 'twill fright</p>
                  <p>Young gentlemen from ſpending of their portions</p>
                  <p>That come to viſit you; whoſe unbounden Riots</p>
                  <p>May enrich you, with their forfeited eſtates:</p>
                  <p>I have a thouſand precepts more.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>But d'ye not</p>
                  <p>Think all this while of Heaven?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis in my wealth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>Or hell?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>A fable to fright fools and children; but</p>
                  <p>I cannot ſtay, my Scrivener does expect me;</p>
                  <p>I'll viſit you another time, ſweet widow,</p>
                  <p>And give you more inſtructions.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>Spare your labour,</p>
                  <p>I ſha'not practice theſe in haſte, and muſt</p>
                  <p>Declare, theſe precepts make not for your welcome.</p>
                  <p>My patience was no vertue all this while.</p>
                  <p>If you but think you have a ſoul, repent:</p>
                  <p>Your rules I am not covetuous to follow;</p>
                  <p>I dare not love 'em.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Live, and be undone then;</p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:35542:5"/>
                  <p>You'll tell me another tale hereafter, widow.—</p>
                  <stage>Exeunt Hornet.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Nurſe and Cloſe.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>If it pleaſe you, here's a letter from Maſter <hi>Startup</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Country-Gentleman.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>What's he?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>A freſh ſuitor of my Nurſes commendations.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Heaven deliver me! What have I ſeen? ſure this</p>
                  <p>Thing was once at Bartholomew-Fire, or ſuch another</p>
                  <p>Furr'd Baboon for all the world: do'ſt know him?</p>
                  <p>And yet why do I ask? the devil would hardly</p>
                  <p>Take acquaintance with him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis maſter <hi>Hornet</hi> the great Uſurer.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hornet?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Nay then my wonder's over; and the devil himſelf</p>
                  <p>Be ſuch another, they may be ſworn brothers, and divide</p>
                  <p>Hell betwixt 'em.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>Who's that you talk on, ſirrah?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Of the diſeaſe that heaven be thank'd has left you,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hornet.</hi> But ſir, I have news for you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Franck?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>I'll hear it in the Garden.—</p>
                  <stage>Exit Hartwel and Cloſe.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>Do you love this Gentleman?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>I hope you move not this as if you doubted;</p>
                  <p>I took him firſt upon your character,</p>
                  <p>Into my good opinion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>But things alter;</p>
                  <p>What then I thought him, I delivered you,</p>
                  <p>Nor ſince hath he deſerv'd a leſs eſteem</p>
                  <p>In his own perſon: but the circumſtance</p>
                  <p>Is not the ſame; his fortune I have examined,</p>
                  <p>Which riſes not to ſuch a value I</p>
                  <p>Did apprehend it; it becomes my care,</p>
                  <p>Being at one gift to depart with thee</p>
                  <p>And my eſtate, to look for one whoſe purſe</p>
                  <p>May carry a proportion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>Make me not</p>
                  <p>Imagine you would wed me to a heap</p>
                  <p>Of ſhining duſt, a golden bondage.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>Nor to penury:</p>
                  <p>His birth and education are not unworthy, he's hanſome too:</p>
                  <p>But be not govern'd by your eye too much;</p>
                  <p>Children and age purſue us, and ſome ſtorms</p>
                  <p>Hover about our frail conditions:</p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:35542:6"/>
                  <p>All theſe muſt be provided for: they are not</p>
                  <p>Kiſſes will make our winters warm; and therefore</p>
                  <p>Confident of your obedience, I propound</p>
                  <p>Another to your beſt thoughts.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh my unhappyneſs!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>A Country gentleman of ſpreading fortunes,</p>
                  <p>Young too, and not uncomely; for his breeding,</p>
                  <p>It was not ſpun the fineſt: but his riches</p>
                  <p>Able to guild deformity, and make</p>
                  <p>Even want of wit a vertue, when your life</p>
                  <p>Renders it ſelf more ſweet by your command:</p>
                  <p>His name is Maſter <hi>Startup,</hi> expected</p>
                  <p>Our gueſt to morrow; that's his letter, read it.</p>
                  <p>This may ſeem ſtrange, while it is coming toward you:</p>
                  <p>But when diſcretion comes to examine what</p>
                  <p>A fruitful conſequence attends it, you</p>
                  <p>Will thank me for't.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>But with your pardon, mother:</p>
                  <p>Although I could diſpence with my own thoughts,</p>
                  <p>And frame them to obedience, will this change</p>
                  <p>Be for your honour, or mine own? when ſuch,</p>
                  <p>When ſuch a noble gentleman ſhall boaſt he had</p>
                  <p>With your conſent my liking? or admit</p>
                  <p>That which we gain by riches of the ſecond,</p>
                  <p>Seem to authorize, and may juſtifie</p>
                  <p>The act with ſome: How can it cure the wound,</p>
                  <p>Which the poor heart that loves ſhall find too ſoon,</p>
                  <p>When 'tis neglected, and ſo cruelly,</p>
                  <p>Where it hopes for cheriſhing? Oh think</p>
                  <p>How you did love my father, firſt; and be</p>
                  <p>Now gentle to your daughter: your eſtate</p>
                  <p>Is above needy providence, or grafting</p>
                  <p>Into a new ſtock; it does grow already</p>
                  <p>Fair from his own root, and does want no piecing;</p>
                  <p>Nor are the means of <hi>Hartwel</hi> ſo contemptible.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>No more: when y'ave conſider'd well, you'll ſhape</p>
                  <p>Another anſwer; i'th' mean time diſpoſe</p>
                  <p>Your countenance to entertain this new</p>
                  <p>And able lover: leave the ſatisfaction</p>
                  <p>Of <hi>Hartwel</hi> to my care; he's here, to your chamber.—</p>
                  <stage>Exit Francis.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Hartwel and Cloſe.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>I know not what's the trick on't, nor themſelves yet,</p>
                  <p>But he has a project to employ 'em in.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>I wiſH it well—But do you work your ſelf</p>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:35542:6"/>
                  <p>Into the opinion of the Nurſe, ſhe is</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Major Domo,</hi> and has all the intelligence.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Let me alone, I'll work her, ſir, like wax,</p>
                  <p>To print what form you pleaſe upon her; 'tis</p>
                  <p>A loving croan to me already:</p>
                  <p>I'll ſpeak her fair, and in my drink may marry her.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>Maſter <hi>Hartwel?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>About your buſineſs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>There is a buſineſs, ſir, which I muſt open,</p>
                  <p>And you perhaps will wonder at.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>You prepare my attention.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>You do love my daughter,</p>
                  <p>At leaſt I think ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>If you knew my heart,</p>
                  <p>You might be confident; in her I ſum</p>
                  <p>All my deſires on earth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>Be not ſo fixt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>How, Lady?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>When you have heard me out, perhaps you'll find</p>
                  <p>Your conſent eaſie to call back a promiſe</p>
                  <p>Made to your diſadvantage.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>I acknowledge</p>
                  <p>This makes me wonder; pray interpret Lady,</p>
                  <p>And ſpeak a language I may underſtand;</p>
                  <p>I love your daughter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>But muſt never glory</p>
                  <p>In the reward which you expect ſhould be</p>
                  <p>Her marriage.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>In the number of my actions</p>
                  <p>There is not one that's guilty of ſo much</p>
                  <p>Offence to you, that I ſhould be ſo ſoon</p>
                  <p>Loſt to your favour.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>Have no thought ſo poor,</p>
                  <p>You can deſerve leſs; my opinion</p>
                  <p>Is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>icher laden with your merit then before.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>Now</p>
                  <p>I fear again, this violent turn of praiſe,</p>
                  <p>Makes me ſuſpect my ſtate: if I be fallen,</p>
                  <p>Teach me to know my treſpaſs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>I ne'er look'd</p>
                  <p>With ſo cleer eyes into your worth; and 'twere</p>
                  <p>A ſin to general goodneſs to delay</p>
                  <p>The free reſign of that, your truth may challenge.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>If this be meant, pray pardon my miſtake</p>
                  <p>Of ſomething went before: love made me fear</p>
                  <p>You ſaid I never ſhould enjoy your daughter</p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:35542:7"/>
                  <p>In marriage, which your ſelf ſo late incline to.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>And muſt again repeat, you ſha' not call</p>
                  <p>Her bride.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>Can you forbid this happineſs, and love me?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, ſo dearly, <hi>Hartwel,</hi> I preſent</p>
                  <p>My ſelf to thy affections.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>You amaze me, and fright my underſtanding.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>Does the name</p>
                  <p>Of widow ſound diſpleaſing? I have learn'd</p>
                  <p>Already to obey; my years are not</p>
                  <p>So many with a thought to freeze your blood;</p>
                  <p>I wear no print of time, deep on my brow,</p>
                  <p>Nor have my hairs the innocence of age:</p>
                  <p>Gentlemen active, and of noble birth,</p>
                  <p>Think no diſhonour to beſeech my love,</p>
                  <p>And if they flatter not, commend my perſon:</p>
                  <p>Adde unto this my wealth, no narrow fortune,</p>
                  <p>And without competition, my daughter</p>
                  <p>Depending on my love, whoſe portion muſt</p>
                  <p>Flow from my bounty, or be nothing: make</p>
                  <p>A ſober apprehenſion of this Tender,</p>
                  <p>And think I was not able to ſuppreſs</p>
                  <p>Theſe flames of love increaſe ſtill by your vertues:</p>
                  <p>This minute quit all hopes of <hi>Frances,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Whoſe mother will admit no Rival; 'tis</p>
                  <p>Within your own election to be happy:</p>
                  <p>My love accepted comes with fair attendance;</p>
                  <p>Deny'd, you haſten your own exile; think on't,</p>
                  <p>To morrow ſometime, I'll expect your anſwer.—</p>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>What have I heard? Was it her Mother ſpake thus?</p>
                  <p>As Pilgrimes by miſtake of ſome ſmall path,</p>
                  <p>Having told many weary ſteps, at night</p>
                  <p>When their hopes flatters 'em they are not far</p>
                  <p>From ſome kind entertainment, finde themſelves</p>
                  <p>Loſt in a wilderneſs; ſo am I miſerable:</p>
                  <p>Thus Love delights to wound and ſee us bleed,</p>
                  <p>He were a gentle god to kill indeed.—</p>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <trailer>Finis Actus Primi.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="act">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:35542:7"/>
               <head>Actus Secundus.</head>
               <stage>Enter Nurſe and Cloſe.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>WO'd thou wo'dſt ſpeak a good word for me: I am</p>
                  <p>Weary of my indentures: I like a fool was in good hope</p>
                  <p>He ſhould have married Miſtreſs <hi>Frances.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>He's a begger; ſhe his wife? no, Maſter <hi>Startup</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Is the man, the man of lands and mony.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Into whoſe ſervice if I could wriggle my ſelf, a</p>
                  <p>Word of thy mouth does it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>I muſt tell you by the way, he is little better then a fool.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>The fitter for her husband, and my maſter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Y'are i'th' right, he's innocent to your hands, and</p>
                  <p>You may ſoon come to nonage his eſtate</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>VVhich if I do, thou ſha't want no petticoats,</p>
                  <p>All's thine own.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>VVhat?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>VVhy all that I can beg, borrow or ſteal from him:</p>
                  <p>VVhat ſhould he do with ſo much riches? I'd perſwade my young Miſtreſs, after the firſt year, to put him to his penſion: he ſhould pay for's diet; and after a month or two, for every time he comes aloft. Hang him, Cuckow-pintle.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſ.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, let her begin betimes, if ſhe mean to rule the roaſt: I'll give her Documents; and be you ſure you ſtick cloſe to your Miſtriſs; there's ſomething to be got that way.</p>
                  <stage>Enter Hartwel and Playfair.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Excellent Verges!</p>
                  <p>How I do love thy documents! I but he's here,</p>
                  <p>I'll not be ſeen with thee; farewell:</p>
                  <p>At night we'll talk the reſt over a ſack-poſſet.—</p>
                  <stage>Exit Cloſe.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>I will uſe this advantage to over-hear a little.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>You tell me ſtrange things; is it poſſible</p>
                  <p>The widow her ſelf loves you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>VVould I had reaſon but to ſuſpect.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:35542:8"/>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>Turn Colt again; this love will kill's all:</p>
                  <p>And can ſhe make no choice, but where her daughter</p>
                  <p>Has the ſame longing? not her dancing days done yet?</p>
                  <p>VVhy there's no remedy, you muſt love her.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>How? and violate my faith to <hi>Frances?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou wilt not be ſo much an infidel,</p>
                  <p>To think I mean thou ſhouldſt forſake the wench.</p>
                  <p>Tell me the mother a fine tale of love,</p>
                  <p>Print kiſſes on her paper-lip, and hug</p>
                  <p>Her reverend body; any thing but lie with her:</p>
                  <p>VVrite ſonnets on the ivorie tooth afore;</p>
                  <p>Swear ſhe does cough diſtinctly; get a rime</p>
                  <p>To bleſs her when ſhe ſneezes, and cry up</p>
                  <p>The method of her noſe, which ſweats and falls</p>
                  <p>So perpendicular; admire the motion</p>
                  <p>Of her blew eyes that look three ways at once:</p>
                  <p>Praiſe her above thy reaſon, or her daughter,</p>
                  <p>And then ſhe will believe, thou maiſt be mad for her.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>Is this the way to do me good? ſhe comes</p>
                  <p>Too faſt upon me already.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>Let her flie to thee,</p>
                  <p>Thou maiſt clip her wings the ſooner, this ſecures thee:</p>
                  <p>Should you hold off, and play the modeſt creature,</p>
                  <p>Nay but deny as maids do, when they love it,</p>
                  <p>And bending of your hams cry, No forſooth,</p>
                  <p>Profeſs your ſelf, with coxcomb like civility,</p>
                  <p>You are not worthy of her carnal favours,</p>
                  <p>She may believe it; and in very ſpight</p>
                  <p>Marry her daughter to a Citizen;</p>
                  <p>Or ſhould you be ſo mad to think to win her</p>
                  <p>To your firſt choice, withholding your paſſions</p>
                  <p>For Miſtreſs <hi>Frances,</hi> complaining how <hi>Don Cupid</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hath ſacrific'd your heart; you may go hang your ſelf:</p>
                  <p>Go to the Barbers, let him firk your hair up,</p>
                  <p>And ſpend his powder; waſh your ſullen face,</p>
                  <p>And ſtarch your infant, upper-lip to look</p>
                  <p>Like one that would run deſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rate on a widow.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Here's pretious conſpiracie!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>This is the way:</p>
                  <p>At leaſure, you may tell your natural Miſtreſs,</p>
                  <p>Like <hi>Jove</hi> you have but put another ſhape on</p>
                  <p>To cheat the Beldame <hi>Juno.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Foul-mouth raſcal, I'm glad I know your plot.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>I apprehend, th'aſt given me good counſel:</p>
                  <p>I'll watch the firſt occaſion to aſſure,</p>
                  <p>I have prefer'd her in my heart already.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:35542:8"/>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>I'll conjure up a croſs plot, and that quickly,</p>
                  <p>Shall mar your mirth, and pay your fine diſſembling;</p>
                  <p>Are you ſo cunning, my love gameſter?—</p>
                  <stage>Exit Nurſe.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>So I'll take my leave then, y'ave no other ſervice</p>
                  <p>To uſe my ſtay: I have a project, <hi>Hartwel,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That muſt not be neglected.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>May not communicate?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou art ingag'd to wait</p>
                  <p>Upon thine own affair, or I ſhould trouble thee</p>
                  <p>To be an actor in't; thou know'ſt <hi>Hornet.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>He is a ſutor to the widow, and</p>
                  <p>After the rate we caſt the plot, my rival.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>I'll rival him; he ſmothers a poor gentlewoman</p>
                  <p>At home with Sea-coal, and allowes her no</p>
                  <p>More light then ſerves to read in painted cloth,</p>
                  <p>The expoſition of the harlots ſtorie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hartwel,</hi> I love her; and before her Father</p>
                  <p>Dyed, we exchang'd our honeſt hearts; 'tis here</p>
                  <p>To free her from that ſlavery ſhe lives in</p>
                  <p>Under the iron-hearted Jaylor, elſe</p>
                  <p>I ſhall repent my aim; he broods upon</p>
                  <p>Her portion, but I have a trick may ſpoil</p>
                  <p>His hatching of young bags; thou ſhalt know all</p>
                  <p>Hereafter; to the widow, <hi>Hartwol:</hi> I am</p>
                  <p>For ſtate-affairs; be faithful, and pray for me.</p>
                  <p>We muſt be bold: farewell, if ſomething hit,</p>
                  <p>We'll laugh in ſpight of <hi>Dives</hi> and the Devil.—</p>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Belamy, Frances, Cloſe, Startup.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>This is the thing, ſir, that muſt carry away</p>
                  <p>The garland; they have given him a cup or two</p>
                  <p>Of ſack, and he has the prettieſt humour,</p>
                  <p>He does ſo whiſtle out his complement:</p>
                  <p>He wears his feather like the captain of</p>
                  <p>A country team, and would become a horſe-coller</p>
                  <p>Rarely; I do not think, but were he put to't</p>
                  <p>With little ſwitching, he would draw the Cart well.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>Sweet Lady, I am your humble ſervant; 'tis well known what I am, where I live; my father dyed ſince I was of age, and left me a younger brothers portion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>A younger brother?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>Sweet Lady, I know what you would ſay, my father had no more children; but I ſpeak modeſtly of my eſtate; I have land enough for two or three wives; I have a horſe in Town; your daughter ſhall ride behind me: Sweet Lady, did you ever ſee the country?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:35542:9"/>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>What country, ſir?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>VVhy, any country living: ſweet Lady, I am your humble ſervant; if you love hawking, hunting, or drinking, there be good fellows will bear you company. Is there any good Tobacco in <hi>London?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Virginia.</hi> Tobacco grows here.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>Sweet ſir, I am your humble ſervant, you ſeem to be a gentleman will fetch me a pipe: there's half a piece, if I be not troubleſome: perhaps, ſweet Lady, you do not love it: if it offend you, let it alone.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>A very pretious widgen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>La, la, la, lere.</p>
                  <stage>Sings and Dances.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>You dance well, ſir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>He has a ſtrong back, I warrant him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>Sweet Lady, is this your daughter?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Ask that queſtion now?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>I was her mother, ſir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>That may be too; what gentleman is that? ſweet ſir, I am your humble ſervant likewiſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>You are too humble, ſir, to ſtoop ſo low;</p>
                  <p>It would become my duty.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>Sweet ſir, 'tis all one; a leg or an arm is not caſt away among friends: I am a Country-Gentleman, all the world knows; ſweet ſir, I have no buſineſs in Town.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>I thought you came to ſee my daughter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>That may be too; ſweet Lady, pray excuſe me, I ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour your fair daughter; for I know as well as another, what belongs to a gentlewoman: ſhe's not the firſt ſweet Lady I have lov'd i'th' way of Matrimony.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>Were you ever married?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>Sweet ſir, no; all men are not alike.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>For ſome are fools.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>Sweet ſir, I do confeſs it;</p>
                  <p>But wit is never good till it be bought,</p>
                  <p>They ſay; there are very good wits in Town,</p>
                  <p>I have brought money a purpoſe with me to buy;</p>
                  <p>If any will ſell me a good pennyworth,</p>
                  <p>I'll give him a hundred pieces, becauſe</p>
                  <p>I would carry a little down into the Country.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>Is there a dearth in your Country?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>Sweet ſir, there's plenty.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Of wild-o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ts; I heard you had much to ſow ſtill.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>My Tenants have, ſweet ſir, but 'tis all one;</p>
                  <p>This Lady ſhall be Lord o'the Soil: I wo'nt</p>
                  <p>Give any man ſix pence for a buſhel of mony.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh brave ſack!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:35542:9"/>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>I am a gentleman, my Father was a Yeoman;</p>
                  <p>But that's all one, ſweet Lady: howſoever I am yours,</p>
                  <p>And every limb is at your ſervice;</p>
                  <p>My hands ſhall walk, my feet ſhall run.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>Away, away.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>By this bright gold they ſhall.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>He keeps his oath.—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>Not run?</p>
                  <p>My Grand-father was a Noblemans Footman, and</p>
                  <p>Indeed he run his Country; my Father did</p>
                  <p>Outrun the Conſtable.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>And he, ſweet Lady,</p>
                  <p>Being his fathers iſſue, muſt run naturally.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>If I live.—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>He'll run himſelf out of all.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>Not run,</p>
                  <p>Sweet Lady? if you have occaſion to uſe me,</p>
                  <p>I wo'nt ſtand upon my feet.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>No, ſir?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay I'll ſtand upon my head, ſweet Lady,</p>
                  <p>To do you courteſie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Then his heels were upwards.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>Pleaſe you, a ſorry dinner ſtays for you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>Sweet Lady, I am your ſervant; will this Gentleman dine with us?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>I'll prevail with Maſter <hi>Hartwel.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>D'ye know what you have done? he's rival</p>
                  <p>Miſtreſs; why, d'ye mean to invite him?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>Sweet ſir, I invite nobody; if you love</p>
                  <p>Any body here.—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>What then?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>Sweet ſir,</p>
                  <p>I ſha'not take it kindly, I do not uſe</p>
                  <p>To quarrel.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>When y'are beaten, ſir, he ſha'not wrong you:</p>
                  <p>Then lay lay him o'er the face.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>Sweet ſir,</p>
                  <p>'Tis dinner-time, fair Lady.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>Maſtert <hi>Hartwel?</hi>—</p>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>I had a great mind to have him beaten;</p>
                  <p>But he's not valiant at meals: would I</p>
                  <p>Were hired to beat him hanſomly after dinner,</p>
                  <p>And make him thank me for't; I'll have ſome plot</p>
                  <p>Upon your pretious body, my ſweet ſir.—</p>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:35542:10"/>Enter Hornet and Doctor, Playfaire's Brother.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>You <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ll me wonders, Doctor.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Doct.</speaker>
                  <p>I have cur'd</p>
                  <p>Her melancholy; but ſhe's o't' other ſide</p>
                  <p>Now extream merry, dance and ſing, all air.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis ſtrange methinks, nothing, but extremities:</p>
                  <p>Good Maſter Doctor, could you not have par'd</p>
                  <p>Her t'other leaden humour?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Doct.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, I could not</p>
                  <p>Kill the malignity of her melancholy</p>
                  <p>Another way: extreamities muſt be cur'd</p>
                  <p>With extreme applications: my next work</p>
                  <p>Shall be to abate this levity of her brain,</p>
                  <p>To qualifie her ſpleen, ſir, by degrees;</p>
                  <p>So ſtate her body in that modeſt temper</p>
                  <p>She was poſſeſt of.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>I complain'd before</p>
                  <p>Of quietneſs; now ſhe's all noiſe and madneſs,</p>
                  <p>By your deſcription.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Doct.</speaker>
                  <p>You muſt have patience</p>
                  <p>A month or ſo, ſhe is not mad but merry;</p>
                  <p>Some ſtange figaries: you muſt underſtand,</p>
                  <p>I have open'd, ſir, her fancie, wherein lay</p>
                  <p>All her imaginations confus'd,</p>
                  <p>And of a heap, ſmother'd for want of vent;</p>
                  <p>And now the ſpirits that were impriſon'd</p>
                  <p>Ruſh out, which cauſeth all her faculties</p>
                  <p>Before oppreſt, to exerciſe themſelves</p>
                  <p>So unexpectedly, as the agitation of her tongue</p>
                  <p>Soon will manifeſt: ſhe's here.</p>
                  <stage>Enter Neece.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neece.</speaker>
                  <p>Unkle, how does your body? you appear</p>
                  <p>As lean as Lent: I've a great mind to dance</p>
                  <p>About a Maypole; ſhall we?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>She is mad.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neece.</speaker>
                  <p>This Doctor has ſo tickled me,</p>
                  <p>I cannot chuſe but laugh; ha, ha, ha:</p>
                  <p>Unkle, if you'll procure a diſpenſarion</p>
                  <p>To marry me your ſelf, deduct the charges</p>
                  <p>Out of my portion: I'll have no other</p>
                  <p>Husband; I could affect an old man now</p>
                  <p>With all my heart.</p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:35542:10"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An old man with a bed full of bones,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Turn to me hony and give me a kiſs,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Unkle, when did you put on a clean ſhirt?</p>
                  <p>Not ſince your wife dyed; that was a pretty ſhift.</p>
                  <p>Indeed I dream'd o'th' devil the laſt night;</p>
                  <p>They ſay 'tis good luck: d'ye not know him, Unkle?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>I know the devil!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neece.</speaker>
                  <p>He's a fine old gentleman,</p>
                  <p>And ſomething like you; no ſuch bugbear as</p>
                  <p>The world imagines; you and he'll keep houſe</p>
                  <p>Together one day: but you'll burn ſea-coal too,</p>
                  <p>To ſave charges, and ſtink the poor ſouls ſo.</p>
                  <p>Shall we go hunt to day? I long to ſtrike</p>
                  <p>A Deer; pray lend me a Croſs-Bow, will you, ſir?</p>
                  <p>I'll pay you uſe for't.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And ſtill ſhe cry'd, Shepherd ſhoot home.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Unkle, you are not merry, I pray laugh</p>
                  <p>A little; imagine y'ad undone a widow,</p>
                  <p>Or turn'd an orphan begging now: ha, ha!</p>
                  <p>How many Churches, 'faith, will you build when</p>
                  <p>You dye? I'll have ſix Bells in every Steeple,</p>
                  <p>And they ſhall go to th'tune of Turn again</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Whittington,</hi> who let out his land</p>
                  <p>For nine lives, cauſe it came in by a Cat.</p>
                  <p>Die Unkle, die, at all adventures.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Why does ſhe talk of dying? ſhe's ſtark mad;</p>
                  <p>Could you not put into the next receipt,</p>
                  <p>Something to make her ſleep well</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Doct.</speaker>
                  <p>Opium.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>In a good quantity.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Doct.</speaker>
                  <p>I could ſo proportion it,</p>
                  <p>She ſhould not wake at all to trouble you:</p>
                  <p>I did it for a Merchants wife laſt week,</p>
                  <p>Which lov'd a Knight. A great man not long ſince,</p>
                  <p>Was weary of his Counteſs; and I cur'd him</p>
                  <p>So artificially of the diſeaſe.—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>She hears.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Doct.</speaker>
                  <p>But collects nothing, yet her ſences</p>
                  <p>Are ſcattered.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neece.</speaker>
                  <p>You ſhall give towards the building</p>
                  <p>Of <hi>Pauls</hi>—Nothing: ſee the mony firſt</p>
                  <p>Laid out that's given already; it were much</p>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:35542:11"/>
                  <p>Sin to bely the dead; but 'tis no matter,</p>
                  <p>You may be as famous, ſir, for pulling down</p>
                  <p>The Pariſh; for the Church will fall of't ſelf,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>With a ding dong Bell.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Why did they put the poor fellow in priſon?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Whom? what fellow?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neece.</speaker>
                  <p>Why the Corn-cutter,</p>
                  <p>Poor gentleman he meant the City</p>
                  <p>No harm; his feet were weary, and that made him</p>
                  <p>In every ſtreet cry out, Have ye any Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ns</p>
                  <p>I'your head or toes?</p>
                  <stage>Enter Purſivant.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pur.</speaker>
                  <p>Which is Maſter <hi>Horn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Ha! with me?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pur.</speaker>
                  <p>A word, ſir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neece.</speaker>
                  <p>Prethee what's he? he comes to borrow money</p>
                  <p>On his wives wedding-ring, or his childs whiſtle now:</p>
                  <p>You may ſee by his noſe, he has no land, he looks</p>
                  <p>As hungry as a Hawk: what do you dream on?</p>
                  <p>Or what Ladies tympany is your next cure?</p>
                  <p>Or whoſe ſtate body muſt be rectified</p>
                  <p>With your quaint gliſter?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pur.</speaker>
                  <p>There is no diſputing, I muſt attend you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>I am ſent for by a Purſivant: the King?</p>
                  <p>Alas, I am undone, I never ſaw him;</p>
                  <p>How ſhould he know me? a poor wretch.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Doct.</speaker>
                  <p>Is't not</p>
                  <p>Some complaint? think.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>That's my fear, there be</p>
                  <p>Too many Knaves i'th' world; and a man cannot</p>
                  <p>Grow rich, but one ſtate-ſurgeon or other</p>
                  <p>Muſt practice on his purſe: before this Lord</p>
                  <p>One veyn is opened, in t'other Court</p>
                  <p>So many ounces he muſt bleed again.</p>
                  <p>Let me ſee: all the treaſon I committed,</p>
                  <p>Is, that I ſhifted houſes; for I took</p>
                  <p>Delight to cozen him of his ſubſidies.</p>
                  <p>I live obſcurely, to avoid</p>
                  <p>Taxations: I never paid the Church</p>
                  <p>Her ſuperſtitious tythes, nor come to trouble</p>
                  <p>Sermons, for fear of homilies before,</p>
                  <p>That beg for burning.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neece.</speaker>
                  <p>Why how now, Uncle? Is your Scrivener broke,</p>
                  <p>You talk ſuch lamentation?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:35542:11"/>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>I am ſent for</p>
                  <p>To the King, Neece, and ſhall be made a beggar,</p>
                  <p>As <hi>I</hi> was born: <hi>I</hi> ſee my Chattels ſeiz'd;</p>
                  <p>This Cheſt is ranſack'd, and that bag deflour'd;</p>
                  <p>My dore ſeal'd up; and with this hungry meſſenger</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> am already marching to the Fleet</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neece.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, and you be at that ward, <hi>I</hi> leave you.</p>
                  <p>Maſty, farewel: pray do not bite my Uncle</p>
                  <p>Too hard; and ſo <hi>I</hi> leave you all to th' mercy</p>
                  <p>Of the Bear-Garden.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Beſt make faſt her chamber.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neece.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I, I,</hi> curſed Dog: and</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Set a thouſand guards about her,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Love will find out a way.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Doct.</speaker>
                  <p>Wo'nt ſome money qualifie your haſte,</p>
                  <p>And give him time to appear?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pur.</speaker>
                  <p>Good Mr. Doctor,</p>
                  <p>Teach your Apothecary: <hi>Galen</hi> nor</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hippocrates</hi> can perſwade me from my duty.</p>
                  <p>Will you go, ſir? or ſhall <hi>I</hi> certifie?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Go! <hi>I</hi> muſt go.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Doct.</speaker>
                  <p>Have comfort, ſir: this cloud</p>
                  <p>May ſoon blow over.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, when <hi>I</hi>'m blown up:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> read impriſonment in his very looks,</p>
                  <p>And all my gold confiſcate.</p>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Nurſe and Startup.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> heard her ſay, ſhe would walk up to her chamber:</p>
                  <p>The trick was but to teach him whither he</p>
                  <p>Should follow, who as nimbly apprehended,</p>
                  <p>To acquaint her with his new affections.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> did this for your good, that Mrs. <hi>Francis,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Whom <hi>I</hi>'ll ſend preſently to you, may be</p>
                  <p>Convinc'd in <hi>Hartwel</hi>'s falſhood, and tranſplant</p>
                  <p>Her love on you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>This will be excellent!</p>
                  <p>So ſhall we ſtrangle him in his own nooſe,</p>
                  <p>And he ne'er know who hurt him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi>'ll looſe no time, you know my inſtructions.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> almoſt had forgot; there is a caſt</p>
                  <p>Of angels more.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>They are not caſt away.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>If thou doſt fear they'll drown, Nurſe, <hi>I</hi> can give</p>
                  <p>Thee lighter, <hi>I</hi> have ſome want weight.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:35542:12"/>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi>f you have an evil angel about you, your buſineſs will thrive the better, when 'tis departed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>There, Mother of the Maids.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Now all the good ones wait upon your worſhip.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>Theſe things that go to and again, muſt have</p>
                  <p>Their fees, they'll never ſpeak in our cauſe elſe.</p>
                  <stage>Enter Frances.</stage>
                  <p>Aha, ſweet ſir! we'll be too cunning for you.</p>
                  <p>She's come already: ſweet Lady, how do ye do?</p>
                  <p>Y'are melancholy, you ſhall have ſome cauſe</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi>f <hi>I</hi> can help you to't; if you be ſad</p>
                  <p>Becauſe <hi>I</hi> love you as <hi>I</hi> do, be merry</p>
                  <p>Again: there's no man cares a button for you</p>
                  <p>Beſides my ſelf.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> am very ill befriended.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>You are deceiv'd in ſome body, and me too;</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> love you <hi>I</hi> confeſs, but how? not for</p>
                  <p>Want of a Miſtreſs; <hi>I</hi> came not a woing</p>
                  <p>For ſuch neceſſity, although you have</p>
                  <p>So little wit, to believe ſomething that</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> know concerning t'other party.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>How's this?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>Tell me, have you opinion, ſweet Lady,</p>
                  <p>That any man beſides my ſelf does love</p>
                  <p>This face of yours? but underſtand, <hi>I</hi>'ll mak't</p>
                  <p>Appear, and preſently.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>VVhy <hi>I</hi> dare ſhew my face:</p>
                  <p>My glaſs cannot ſo much deceive me, ſir:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> ſhou'd be aſham'd it ſhould appear.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay I am</p>
                  <p>For that, a your ſide; d'ye conceive me right?</p>
                  <p>A worſe face will become the Country, and</p>
                  <p>Shew well enough at the muſtering; but that</p>
                  <p>You ſhould be ſuch an aſs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>This is plain Courtſhip.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Start.</speaker>
                  <p>Be ſure you underſtand me, and you do not</p>
                  <p>Repent it, I dare give one of theſe ears.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>You do not threaten me?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>Underſtand me right,</p>
                  <p>But if I do, and will threaten you agen,</p>
                  <p>Becauſe you ſhall live long to ſee your folly,</p>
                  <p>And what a Coxcomb you have made your ſelf,</p>
                  <p>To love a man that is a ſuitor to</p>
                  <p>Your mother: ha, ha!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:35542:12"/>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>VVhom do you mean?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>E'en Mr. <hi>Hartwel:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Are you ſuch a buzzard</p>
                  <p>You cannot ſee't? then you ſhall hear it: ſtep</p>
                  <p>Behind theſe hangings, and he'll juſtifie it.</p>
                  <stage>Enter Hartwel and Mrs. Bellamy.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> have conſider'd perfectly; and if</p>
                  <p>You will vouchſafe me hearing, dare pour forth</p>
                  <p>My heart, which full of love tenders it ſelf</p>
                  <p>To your acceptance: <hi>I</hi> acknowledge, Lady,</p>
                  <p>My paſſions are but young, for could <hi>I</hi> hope</p>
                  <p>You ſhould with ſo much favour look upon me?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>But may <hi>I</hi> credit this?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>But to ſuſpect,</p>
                  <p>Were an injuſtice to my faith, which looks</p>
                  <p>Upon your vertue with as much religion</p>
                  <p>As love is able to receive: your age</p>
                  <p>Hath ſtruck a reverence into my eye;</p>
                  <p>And what you want of youth and ſpring upon you,</p>
                  <p>Your wiſdom richly ſatisfies. Thoſe characters</p>
                  <p>Which time hath written on your careful forehead,</p>
                  <p>Are but his envie, and your ornament,</p>
                  <p>VVhen it ſhall come to paſs by your example,</p>
                  <p>That youth ſhall be eſteem'd an infancy,</p>
                  <p>And women never ripe for love or marriage</p>
                  <p>VVithout your age upon them; 'tis a fault</p>
                  <p>That men not guided by the tract of reaſon,</p>
                  <p>But heat and wantonneſs of blood, run giddy</p>
                  <p>To ſeal ſuch weighty covenants; better 'twere</p>
                  <p>The world ſhould end in our Virginitie,</p>
                  <p>Then ſpin it ſelf more length, by inconſiderate</p>
                  <p>And haſty marriages.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>Have you already</p>
                  <p>Retriv'd the affection which purſu'd my daughter?</p>
                  <p>Shall I believe no ſeeds of love remain,</p>
                  <p>VVhich may grow up and ripen with repentance?</p>
                  <p>For this exchange <hi>I</hi> do allow you, ſir,</p>
                  <p>The conſideration of my fortune, which</p>
                  <p>Might in it ſelf incline you to accept me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>That is but an attendant, as you uſe it,</p>
                  <p>I muſt confeſs a welcome one, although</p>
                  <p>The mind is the firſt beauty which true love</p>
                  <p>Aſpires to, when 'tis waited on with perſon</p>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:35542:13"/>
                  <p>And an eſtate; it comes with greater priviledge</p>
                  <p>To win upon's: <hi>I</hi> do not wiſh you, Lady,</p>
                  <p>Raſhly believe what <hi>I</hi> profeſs, but meaſure</p>
                  <p>My ſervice by the tryal; <hi>I</hi>'ll expect,</p>
                  <p>And write your ſmiles a competent reward,</p>
                  <p>Till time and your demand demonſtrate me,</p>
                  <p>Although not equal to your full deſervings,</p>
                  <p>Yet one that has ambition to be thought</p>
                  <p>Not too unworthy.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>And <hi>I</hi> gueſs ere long,</p>
                  <p>Such an occaſion will preſent it ſelf.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>Till then have <hi>Hartwel</hi> in your loving memory,</p>
                  <p>Who wiſhes no more happyneſs of life</p>
                  <p>Then to be call'd yours.—</p>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>VVhat have <hi>I</hi> underſtood?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>Will you believe me another time, ſweet Lady?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>It is not he, ſome devil does but cozen us,</p>
                  <p>And mock our ſence, with theſe phantaſtick bodies.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hartwel!</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay 'tis the man, <hi>I</hi> hope you'll be converted,</p>
                  <p>And think a Country-Gentleman worth favour</p>
                  <p>That brought you to this knowledge; <hi>I</hi> deſerve.—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>My curſes for this black diſcovery:</p>
                  <p>VVhereas before 'twas not impoſſible</p>
                  <p>In time <hi>I</hi> might be brought to pitty thee;</p>
                  <p>Henceforth <hi>I</hi>'ll look upon thee as my ſins,</p>
                  <p>And beg as much forgiveneſs, that <hi>I</hi> knew thee.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, but d'ye hear?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>Die quickly, and be forgotten.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>This is very fine, ſweet Lady!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>My mother! Oh my fate! ſee me no more,</p>
                  <p>And <hi>I</hi>'ll forgive thee.—</p>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Is</hi>'t come to this? <hi>I</hi> ſee</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> am a fool, and there's no remedy—</p>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <trailer>Finis Actus Secundi.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="act">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:35542:13"/>
               <head>Actus Tertius.</head>
               <stage>Enter Startup and Nurſe.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Fie, fie, <hi>I</hi> am aſham'd on you, a Gentleman</p>
                  <p>Of your high promiſing, and be put off</p>
                  <p>So ſlightly?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>VVhy Nurſe? what would you have me do?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Do? <hi>I</hi> would have you do—ſomething; a man of your ability, and cannot turn and wind a woman?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>You would not have wiſhed me</p>
                  <p>To have put her to't behind the hangings?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>You ſhould have been round with her.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> was round</p>
                  <p>With her; <hi>I</hi> call'd her aſs, <hi>I</hi> think, and coxcomb:</p>
                  <p>Unleſs <hi>I</hi> ſhould have given her the lye,</p>
                  <p>And call'd her whore, <hi>I</hi> could not be more round with her.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> do not mean that way.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>And ſhe call'd me,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> think, her—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>VVhat?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>Why no worſe then all her ſins; heaven forgive her,</p>
                  <p>She has the more to anſwer; nay ſhe did</p>
                  <p>Not ſtick to bid me dye too, in that deſperate</p>
                  <p>Eſtate.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Come, you ſhall take another courſe.</p>
                  <stage>Enter Cloſe.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>What ailes my Maſters ſweet-heart? is ſhe frighted?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> met and ask'd her for my Maſter, and</p>
                  <p>She turn'd tail like a hound had loſt the ſent:</p>
                  <p>There's ſomething in the wind: my three pil'd worſhipful,</p>
                  <p>Are you there, with my Lady o'the larder?</p>
                  <p>Now in that poſture, do not they two look like</p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:35542:14"/>
                  <p>A fine Brick-Houſe and a Thatch'd-Barn i'th' Country,</p>
                  <p>Laying their heads together? without doubt</p>
                  <p>Some pretious conſultation: what poeſie</p>
                  <p>Will fit his joynt ring, or how many yards</p>
                  <p>Of Holland without ſeaming-lace will make</p>
                  <p>His Miſtreſs ſmock: they have ſpied me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cloſe,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Come hither; nay he's faithful, and one that</p>
                  <p>Has a deſire to ſerve you: you may truſt him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Your worſhip may truſt me abed w'ye;</p>
                  <p>Have had an itch this great while, ſir, a kinde</p>
                  <p>Of longing, to be one of your appurtenances;</p>
                  <p>I have ſome faults, and I'll confeſs 'em: I have</p>
                  <p>A humour now and then when I am asked</p>
                  <p>A queſtion, to tell truth, though I be chid for't;</p>
                  <p>And I do not love blows: you may ſooner beat</p>
                  <p>My brains out, then a word of flattery:</p>
                  <p>I cannot batten upon commendation,</p>
                  <p>Without my wages, nor be valiant</p>
                  <p>Upon ſmall beer; I am not overmuch</p>
                  <p>Given to be drunk, but I've a trick o'th' Dutchman,</p>
                  <p>To do your buſineſs as well drunk as ſober:</p>
                  <p>I have not impudence enough to pimp</p>
                  <p>For you; but I have a gift, I can ſay nothing</p>
                  <p>As well as your chaplain; I ſuck'd ſecreſie</p>
                  <p>From mine own mother, once a baudy Mid-wife:</p>
                  <p>I was born upon Shrove-Tueſday, and ſhall be</p>
                  <p>Now and then given to rebellion:</p>
                  <p>My fleſh will once a year riſe at a chambermaid,</p>
                  <p>If none ſuch take me down; I ſhall in malice</p>
                  <p>And deep revenge, fling out upon <hi>May-Day</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Among the Apprentices without fear or wit:</p>
                  <p>If you chance to be arreſted, I dare kill</p>
                  <p>Any thing, but a Sergeant; he's lapt</p>
                  <p>In law, a wearing ſtronger far then buff:</p>
                  <p>If any gentleman ne'er ſo much provok'd,</p>
                  <p>Prick him between the ſeams, or knock his brains out,</p>
                  <p>Which is the ſurer way (for moſt a theſe</p>
                  <p>Vermine, would fain be kill'd) he is ſure to take</p>
                  <p>His leave at the Towns end; his breakfaſt is</p>
                  <p>Tyed up, and ſtays for him, neer my Lord Mayors</p>
                  <p>Banquetting houſe, made for the City-progreſs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>I like his humour.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay he has a ſconce,</p>
                  <p>And ſhall be of our counſel; afterward,</p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:35542:14"/>
                  <p>Your worſhip may entertain him: Look you <hi>Cloſe,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There is a plot to help this Gentleman</p>
                  <p>At night, when they are abed: and if you went</p>
                  <p>To bed betimes, to avoid ſuſpition,</p>
                  <p>'Twere never the worſe; I'll ſay you are not well:</p>
                  <p>D'ye mark? this honeſt Gentleman ſhall be</p>
                  <p>Let into Mrs. <hi>Frances</hi> bedchamber.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Without her knowledge?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>You ſhall only attend</p>
                  <p>To give him notice from me when to come,</p>
                  <p>And watch about the houſe, he may get off</p>
                  <p>Without diſcovery; this is all.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>So, ſo, I ſha' not keep the door.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>I can do that.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Let me alone to give you notice who</p>
                  <p>Stirs about houſe.</p>
                  <stage>Enter Hartwel.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Away, 'tis Maſter <hi>Hartwel,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>We'll not be ſeen together,</p>
                  <p>Go your ways.—</p>
                  <stage>Exit Nurſe and Startup.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>A fooliſh knave and baud, that do want nothing</p>
                  <p>But carting; I would ſooner ſee that Tryumph</p>
                  <p>Then all the Pageants a day after <hi>Simon</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And <hi>Jude,</hi> when the fine City goes a feaſting.</p>
                  <p>Oh ſir, I have news; yes, they are gone, brave news,</p>
                  <p>Your gentlewoman can hold out no longer:</p>
                  <p>This night there will be a ſtratagem; the governeſs</p>
                  <p>Old madam <hi>Humpeapampe,</hi> the Nurſe, has promis'd</p>
                  <p>To admit the Country Gentleman, when all</p>
                  <p>Are abed, into her chamber; yes, your Miſtriſſes:</p>
                  <p>I'm o'the plot to lie perdue, and give</p>
                  <p>The word if any fire-lock approach;</p>
                  <p>The reſt imagine: if he have not art to</p>
                  <p>Perſwade her to the feat with him, yet there</p>
                  <p>Be tricks, and he may be ſurpriz'd i'th' chamber,</p>
                  <p>And ſhe may be compell'd to marry him, in</p>
                  <p>Her own defence: there have been ſuch devices.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>Does ſhe conſent?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>She is betray'd to't, Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou wo't not be ſo baſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>And I had meant it,</p>
                  <p>I ne'er had told you this: can you make uſe</p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:35542:15"/>
                  <p>Of this intelligence?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>Th'art my honeſt ſervant.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>I promis'd to be his.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>I have it, canſt</p>
                  <p>By any means procure me but his cloathes?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>With eaſe: he'll go to bed betimes, to void</p>
                  <p>Suſpition, that's a part of our deſigne.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>I could not wiſh a happier opportunity,</p>
                  <p>To try how ſhe affects this gaudy fool,</p>
                  <p>And cleer my faith to her; which her mothers watch</p>
                  <p>Will not permit: ſhe has I fear obſerv'd</p>
                  <p>My new familiarity with the mother,</p>
                  <p>Which I'm compell'd to, and muſt cure this way:</p>
                  <p>Fail me not, <hi>Cloſe,</hi> and propound thy own</p>
                  <p>Reward.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Tell me your purpoſe, and let my wit</p>
                  <p>Diſpoſe of him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>Proſper me Love in this.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>And you fall to your prayers</p>
                  <p>With good Love look about us, I ſhall ſuſpect</p>
                  <p>You will not thrive: you ſhould go to a wench</p>
                  <p>As gentlemen fall to Oyſters, without ceremony,</p>
                  <p>Or ſaying grace; devotion will ſpoil all.—</p>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Playfaire and Doctor his brother.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Doct'.</speaker>
                  <p>Right as an arrow.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>Witty engineer:</p>
                  <p>But was ſhe taken with the plot?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Doct.</speaker>
                  <p>I was</p>
                  <p>Compell'd to frame an outſide of a reaſon,</p>
                  <p>Leſt her own mirth ſhould play the traytor with us,</p>
                  <p>Her ſpleen was ſo dilated; he believes</p>
                  <p>She's mad: which change makes for us.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>Excellent.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Doct.</speaker>
                  <p>And he that you employ'd, the Purſivant,</p>
                  <p>Shew'd ſuch a ſurly raſcal, the poor Uſurer</p>
                  <p>Trembled as Bauds beneath the laſh.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>He comes then.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Doct.</speaker>
                  <p>With as much joy, as to receive a hanging.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>He would be whipt, and ſay his prayers at <hi>Pauls</hi> in a white ſheet.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Doct.</speaker>
                  <p>That were penance to him:</p>
                  <p>Nay he would pay as much as he ſhould fine</p>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:35542:15"/>
                  <p>For Alderman, though half his ſoul went with it,</p>
                  <p>For his <hi>Quietus;</hi> he does apprehend</p>
                  <p>Nothing but earthquakes.</p>
                  <stage>Enter three Lords.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>How I am rampant</p>
                  <p>With the imagination? bid the muſick</p>
                  <p>Be ready, they know all their flouriſhes:</p>
                  <p>But ſhift you quickly—My honourable Lords.—</p>
                  <stage>Exit Doctor.</stage>
                  <p>How they do look like States-men! where's your tooth-pick?</p>
                  <p>Excellent! bear your ſtaff hanſomly; contract</p>
                  <p>Your brow, and look more ſuperciliouſly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 Lord.</speaker>
                  <p>I warrant you for my part.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 Lord.</speaker>
                  <p>We came now from practice.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>Can ye do't with confidence?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 Lord.</speaker>
                  <p>Theſe very cloathes have made me proud already:</p>
                  <p>It was ſome Lords caſt ſute, I'll lay my life.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>3 Lord.</speaker>
                  <p>And mine; it ſmells of honour.</p>
                  <stage>Enter one with perfume.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>More perfume, ſo, ſo; how now man?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 Lord.</speaker>
                  <p>He looks pale; my Lord, how d'ye?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>3 Lord.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, well, I hope 'tis but conceipt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>Of what?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>3 Lord.</speaker>
                  <p>Will the pox lie in cloathes? I cannot tell,</p>
                  <p>I finde ſome alteration in my body</p>
                  <p>Since I ſhifted.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis a meer conceipt;</p>
                  <p>They were an honeſt mans, upon my knowledge,</p>
                  <p>A Captain of the Train'd-Band in the Country:</p>
                  <p>They were bought againſt the general muſter laſt;</p>
                  <p>He wore 'em that day, and moſt carefully ſent 'em up</p>
                  <p>To taſt our <hi>London</hi> lavender.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>3 Lord.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, you have</p>
                  <p>Satisfied me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>Be ſprighful: where's this Prince,</p>
                  <p>Whoſe nod muſt make us double before age?</p>
                  <p>I long to kiſs his hand.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 Lord.</speaker>
                  <p>He's here.</p>
                  <stage>Flouriſh.</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:35542:16"/>Enter Lambert, Playfaire's brother, for the fourth Lord, Sir Poldavis and attendants.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>Now by that ſprig, a pretty lump of Majeſty,</p>
                  <p>No actor could become it half ſo royally:</p>
                  <p>But wilt thou not be out of thy Kings part,</p>
                  <p>And when wine is wanting at the banquet,</p>
                  <p>Call upon drawers, quarrel with your Nobles?</p>
                  <p>Or when we ſhall preſent our man of morgages,</p>
                  <p>Take him aſide, and borrow half a crown</p>
                  <p>To give your whore benevolence, which truſted</p>
                  <p>For you laſt tilting; or be drunk too ſoon,</p>
                  <p>And leave our project in the durt?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lords,</p>
                  <p>This fellow's inſolence muſt be corrected:</p>
                  <p>Diſpoſe him in what priſon you think fit.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>4 Lord.</speaker>
                  <p>He's mad, I think.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                  <p>To Bedlam with him then:</p>
                  <p>Is this a place for fools and madmen? who</p>
                  <p>Admitted him? take him away; ſee you</p>
                  <p>He be well whipt, and let him thank our mercy,</p>
                  <p>Bandog.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>I quake already; excellent <hi>Lambert!</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Cool, cool thy lungs, and whiſper with ſome Lord,</p>
                  <p>Thou wo't be a key too high elſe: good ſir <hi>Poldavis,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Maſter of the houſe, at whoſe coſt we are</p>
                  <p>Entertained!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
                  <p>My part is rotten</p>
                  <p>In my head, doubt not.</p>
                  <stage>Enter Purſivant.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>Is he come?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pur.</speaker>
                  <p>He waits at the firſt chamber.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>Then let the Lutes</p>
                  <p>Begin, and then admit him.</p>
                  <stage>Lutes.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Hornet.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Here's revelling, my purſe muſt be ſqueez'd for't:</p>
                  <p>That's the King, the reſt are bare; how ſupple they are</p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:35542:16"/>
                  <p>I'th' hams? that Courtier has oyled his joynts:</p>
                  <p>He looks this way, they point at me; a rot</p>
                  <p>O'that knaves finger.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 Lord.</speaker>
                  <p>What fellow's this? who waits?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pur.</speaker>
                  <p>It was his Graces pleaſure he was ſent for.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 Lord.</speaker>
                  <p>My good Lord.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>4 Lord.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lord of <hi>Noland,</hi> as you were ſaying.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                  <p>Is this the man whom you ſo much commended for his abilities?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſmell no good from that word ability.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                  <p>Diſcreet, and read i'th' Common-wealth, a man</p>
                  <p>Fit for employment in ſome Embaſſie?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
                  <p>The very ſame.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                  <p>His countenance is promiſing.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
                  <p>If the King</p>
                  <p>Of <hi>Spain</hi> had but his head, that politick head,</p>
                  <p>I know who might go fiſh for the Low-Countries.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                  <p>His garments are but courſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
                  <p>His mind is rich.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>They praiſe me: I am a thouſand pounds the worſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                  <p>Kneel down, thy name?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Gyles Hornet,</hi> your poor creature.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                  <p>We'll knight him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>I do beſeech you, ſir, to ſpare this honour,</p>
                  <p>I am not able to maintain my ſelf;</p>
                  <p>There be more Knights then can live well already.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
                  <p>Neglect his favour?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                  <p>Be it your care</p>
                  <p>To give his body more becoming ornaments,</p>
                  <p>He ſhall be like himſelf then; we will confer</p>
                  <p>More honours on him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>4 Lord</speaker>
                  <p>Do you make haſte, his Grace</p>
                  <p>Will have you new thatch'd; you muſt have rich cloaths</p>
                  <p>Fitting your ſtate and honourable title.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Theſe will be good enough for me, 'las I am not able.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>4 Lord.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay you muſt have them from his Wardrobe, ſir,</p>
                  <p>They'll coſt you nothing; you'll not look in theſe</p>
                  <p>Like a poor Knight of <hi>Windſore.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                  <p>Where be the Ladies, and the Bride?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
                  <p>She's your Graces handmaid; they</p>
                  <p>Are dancing, ſir, within.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                  <p>Direct us to 'em prethee;</p>
                  <p>VVhen he is ready give us knowledge—</p>
                  <stage>Flouriſh. Exeunt.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>4 Lord.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, ſir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>VVhat will become of me?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:35542:17"/>4 Lord.</speaker>
                  <p>You were beſt prepare,</p>
                  <p>Your cloaths will be here preſently; the King</p>
                  <p>VVill ſend to you before y'are ready; caſt</p>
                  <p>Your old skin off: do you not to ſave ſheets</p>
                  <p>And trouble, wrap your ſelfanights i'th' blankets?</p>
                  <p>Or are they aſham'd to ſhew the linings?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Hum; if this be but a preparative for a whipping,</p>
                  <p>VVhat caſe am I in?</p>
                  <stage>Enter Servant with cloaths.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>4 Lord.</speaker>
                  <p>VVell ſaid, now they are come,</p>
                  <p>Be nimble now, and help to ſtrip him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>'Las, muſt I wear this doublet? it would yeild</p>
                  <p>Heaven knows how much to burn.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>4 Lord.</speaker>
                  <p>You may be deſperate</p>
                  <p>VVhen 'tis on, and burn your body with it, ſir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſha'not know my ſelf.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <p>Fit as 'twere made, ſir.</p>
                  <stage>Enter Playfaire.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>Which is ſir <hi>Gyles?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>I am not Knighted yet.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>You have your grace, and may be call'd ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Have I the grace to be a Knight?</p>
                  <p>I am the man you pleaſe to call ſir <hi>Gyles.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>Then I congratulate your happy fortune;</p>
                  <p>Y'are like to be exalted; his Grace talks</p>
                  <p>Much on you; I'll be proud to be your ſervant:</p>
                  <p>Sir <hi>Robert,</hi> a word.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>VVhat gentleman is this?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <p>The Bridegroom, ſir; in great favour I can tell you,</p>
                  <p>And new created by his Highneſs, Baron</p>
                  <p>Of <hi>Landskip;</hi> his living is far off.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>My very good Lord, my breeches are almoſt on.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <p>Here be your keys.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>His Majeſty has pleas'd to ſhine upon</p>
                  <p>A piece of barren earth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>You are too modeſt:</p>
                  <p>The King hath been informed, ſir <hi>Gyles,</hi> you are</p>
                  <p>One of the ableſt men in his Dominions:</p>
                  <p>Should vertue ſtill be cloath'd in rags? advance it</p>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:35542:17"/>
                  <p>To honour and regard: you waſte your brain</p>
                  <p>At home in cheap and low engagements, ſweat</p>
                  <p>Your ſoul out, for a poor and paltry living:</p>
                  <p>Old houſes, let 'em fall to the dull Lord</p>
                  <p>O'th' Manner; ſwitch me up a town together,</p>
                  <p>Or meddle not; this and that ſtrading Acre</p>
                  <p>Not worth your care: ſtudy ſome Monopoly,</p>
                  <p>May ſweep the Kingdom at a ſtroak: deſpiſe</p>
                  <p>A project will not bring in half the City:</p>
                  <p>Find out a way to forfeit all the Charters:</p>
                  <p>Have an exchequer of your own, and keep</p>
                  <p>The Princes round about in penſion:</p>
                  <p>Theſe are becoming buſineſſes, and ſpeak a States-man.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>You do talk ſtrange things, my Lord:</p>
                  <p>So, now my keys, good gentlemen, my keys.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>4 Lord.</speaker>
                  <p>You have 'em, ſir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Cry mercy.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>They are things</p>
                  <p>Material to our buſineſs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>4 Lord.</speaker>
                  <p>And we'll have 'em again:</p>
                  <p>Let me alone, the Barbour has not done yet;</p>
                  <p>When he's i'th' ſuds, we may be more familiar</p>
                  <p>With's worſhips pocket, and return 'em quaintly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>I will account it one of my felicities</p>
                  <p>To be a witneſs of your honour, ſir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh my good Lord of <hi>Landskip.</hi>—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <p>How ſhall we diſpoſe of theſe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>4 Lord.</speaker>
                  <p>The Hangman will not have 'em; and I fear</p>
                  <p>They will corrupt the well; faith give 'em ſtable-room,</p>
                  <p>The are dung already.—</p>
                  <stage>Enter 1 Lord.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 Lord.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lord, the King asks for you; good ſir <hi>Gyles,</hi> 'tis ſo decreed; write me i'th' number of your faithful friends.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>We muſt attend.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>4 Lord.</speaker>
                  <p>Do not yet ſay he's ready,</p>
                  <p>The Barber has a duty to diſpatch,</p>
                  <p>He will be an hour a rubbing, waſhing, powdering:</p>
                  <p>Then I'll attend him to his preſence.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>We ſhall excuſe him ſo long, ſtill your ſervant—</p>
                  <stage>Exit Playfaire and 1 Lord.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>4 Lord.</speaker>
                  <p>The Barber, ſir, attends in the next room.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>I wo'not ſhave.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>4 Lord.</speaker>
                  <p>He fears his throat.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:35542:18"/>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>I never</p>
                  <p>Give above three pence.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>4 Lord.</speaker>
                  <p>Talk not you of charge,</p>
                  <p>You have but yet your welcome; do not you</p>
                  <p>Think, good ſir <hi>Gyles,</hi> but we can ſhave you too.—</p>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Cloſe and Startup.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>Where is he, <hi>Cloſe?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>I told him, ſir,</p>
                  <p>You lay in a chamber o'the t'other ſide</p>
                  <p>The houſe, whither he's gone with his ſword drawn,</p>
                  <p>And curſes of themſelves able to kill you;</p>
                  <p>You did affront him once, and now his Miſtreſs</p>
                  <p>Has quite neglected him, for your love, he thinks;</p>
                  <p>He'll make you an example to all rivals;</p>
                  <p>I'll bring your cloaths t'ye after: yet your fear</p>
                  <p>And running, ſir, will keep you warm enough.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>Honeſt <hi>Cloſe,</hi> thou haſt ſav'd my life.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Death, is he not behind you? this way, good ſir.—</p>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Nurſe and Miſtreſs Frances.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Have you not made a fine choice? I did ever</p>
                  <p>Think he was falſe; your mother did but counterfeit</p>
                  <p>The love-ſick widow, all this while, to try him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>To try him, <hi>Nurſe?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>She told me ſo her ſelf,</p>
                  <p>Aſſuring him the ſtate was hers, and you</p>
                  <p>At her devotion: put him to his choice</p>
                  <p>To take her with the wealth, or you with nothing;</p>
                  <p>What followed you have heard: come, be wiſe yet,</p>
                  <p>And love the Country-Gentleman, that dotes on you;</p>
                  <p>He's rich and half a fool: I'll fetch him to you.—</p>
                  <stage>Exit Nurſe.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>My mother counterfeit? why may not <hi>Hartwel</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Pretend as well as ſhe, fearing her anger</p>
                  <p>And policy, if he refus'd her love?</p>
                  <p>I have obſerv'd ſome ſorrow in his geſture,</p>
                  <p>As he were willing to deliver ſomething,</p>
                  <p>If opportunity would give him leave:</p>
                  <p>He cannot be ſo falſe; now I ſuſpect</p>
                  <p>He does obey ſome dire neceſſity;</p>
                  <p>Twould puzzle a wiſe lover to be ſo</p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:35542:18"/>
                  <p>Severely put to't.</p>
                  <stage>Enter Nurſe and Hartwel diſguis'd.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>On like a bold Captain,</p>
                  <p>Give her a broad ſide, ſhe's within your ſhot;</p>
                  <p>I'll leave you.—</p>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis the fool; why <hi>Nurſe?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, flee not,</p>
                  <p>Before you hear.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis <hi>Hartwel.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>If my voice</p>
                  <p>Betray me not.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>Why in this ſhape? ſome trick in't,</p>
                  <p>He hides his face; I'll put him to't however,</p>
                  <p>Although the hour be unſeaſonable; any time</p>
                  <p>We may expreſs our joy: my <hi>Nurſe</hi> once told me</p>
                  <p>You were not well, and gone to bed: your health</p>
                  <p>Is welcome as mine own; I dare not, ſir,</p>
                  <p>In modeſty preſume to bid you ſtay,</p>
                  <p>And to requite your pains, kind Maſter <hi>Startup.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>She knows me not.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>Forgive me if I bluſh:</p>
                  <p>I have no other way, but to declare</p>
                  <p>My eyes that late frown'd on your love, ſhall ſmile.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>On me?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>On none but you: I have been too</p>
                  <p>Unkindly dealt withal by <hi>Hartwel,</hi> whom</p>
                  <p>How dearly I affected, good heavens knows:</p>
                  <p>But I have read diſcretion to my fancie,</p>
                  <p>And were he here, he ſhould be witneſs of</p>
                  <p>My vows to you, if you accept my heart,</p>
                  <p>And can with equal truth embrace it: I</p>
                  <p>Will chuſe my husband here; you, only you:</p>
                  <p>This Faith is regiſtred in heaven, ſhall challenge</p>
                  <p>From me a wives obedience.</p>
                  <stage>Enter Nurſe, Hartwel Planet-ſtruck.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Away, her mother's up; I would not for</p>
                  <p>A thouſand pound ſhe finde you in this chamber.—</p>
                  <stage>Exit Frances.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>I have undone my ſelf.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Sweet Maſter <hi>Startup</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To your own lodging, take this cloſe lanthorn with ye.</p>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:35542:19"/>
                  <p>Paſſion of me, what makes her riſe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>I will diſcover yet.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Diſcover what?</p>
                  <p>How! Maſter <hi>Hartwel!</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>You have midnight-plots.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh we are wretched miſerable! what have I done?—</p>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh who ſhall lead me to a world where are</p>
                  <p>No women! farewell all: I'll be above</p>
                  <p>Your charms, and finde out death a cure for love.—</p>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <trailer>Finis Actus Tertius.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="act">
               <head>Actus Quartus.</head>
               <stage>Enter Startup and Cloſe.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>WHere are we now? 'tis very cold, why doſt not</p>
                  <p>Lead to ſome houſe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>What at this time of night?</p>
                  <p>All people are abed; the very Owls</p>
                  <p>Are in their dead ſleep: or if we could</p>
                  <p>Be admitted, would you venture a this faſhion,</p>
                  <p>And publiſh your diſgrace? proclaim your ſelf</p>
                  <p>Coward, and lay ſome imputation</p>
                  <p>Upon the place you came from, where your hopes</p>
                  <p>May yet be fair for marriage? this brunt over,</p>
                  <p>To meet a drunkard now were comfortable,</p>
                  <p>Whoſe eyes inflam'd would ſerve inſtead of torches,</p>
                  <p>Or he might ſpit Flap-Dragons from his fire</p>
                  <p>Of Sack, and light us; but no ſober man</p>
                  <p>Conſidering what caſe you are in, ſir,</p>
                  <p>By my conſent ſhould ſee us.—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>Ha, what's that?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Where? where? a fire-Drake?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>Now 'tis gone, 'tis bright</p>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:35542:19"/>
                  <p>Again, is't not a ſpirit? Oh deliver me!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>I have heard ſome ſuch things uſe to walk the Fields.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>What ſhall I do?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Pray, pray, with as much ſtrength</p>
                  <p>As if you had no land, or were confin'd</p>
                  <p>To my Annuity; now I hear no ſpirits,</p>
                  <p>This riches makes us cowards: hide your ſelf,</p>
                  <p>I will go nearer.—</p>
                  <stage>Exit Cloſe.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>Doſt know the devil if thou ſeeſt him, <hi>Cloſe?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A pox a love, if this be the reward on't;</p>
                  <p>Some call it fire, but I find no ſuch matter;</p>
                  <p>I am frozen to the blanket, and my teeth</p>
                  <p>Strike one another, and keep time like hammers;</p>
                  <p>I do believe if they were beaten out,</p>
                  <p>They would make falſe Dice, there's Quick-ſilver in 'em</p>
                  <p>Already by their dancing.</p>
                  <stage>Enter Cloſe.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, where are you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>Here I am, here ſtill.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Y'are a dead man.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>More terrour? what's the matter?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis my Maſter</p>
                  <p>With a dark lanthorn, and purſues us, by</p>
                  <p>This darkneſs; 'tis his voice, wrap your ſelf up,</p>
                  <p>And roul into ſome ditch; flight will betray us.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>I were as good be kil'd, and yet I'll venter.—</p>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis he indeed, and more then I expected:</p>
                  <p>The matters do not fadge well with his Miſtreſs.</p>
                  <stage>Enter Hartwel with a dark lanthorn.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>What a ſweet thing is night! how calm and harmleſs!</p>
                  <p>No whiſpering but of leaves, on which the breath</p>
                  <p>Of heaven plays muſick, to the birds that ſlumber:</p>
                  <p>Here are no objects to betray our ſence</p>
                  <p>To a repentance; nor can women thus</p>
                  <p>Advantag'd by the tapers of the night,</p>
                  <p>Spread their temptations to undo poor man:</p>
                  <p>What a fine book is heaven! which we may read</p>
                  <p>Beſt now when every ſtar is a fair letter:</p>
                  <p>How much they wrong thee, night, that call thee guilty</p>
                  <p>Of rapes and murders? 'tis the day that like</p>
                  <p>A glorious whore ingageth men to act 'em;</p>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:35542:20"/>
                  <p>And taking then the darkneſs to obſcure 'em,</p>
                  <p>We unjuſtly lay the ſhame upon thy brows</p>
                  <p>That art ſo innocent, thou never ſawſt 'em:</p>
                  <p>Befriended with the ſilence I begin</p>
                  <p>To wander; there's no wilderneſs abroad</p>
                  <p>To him, that's loſt at home.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>Who's that?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>One that has ta'en ſome pains for you to night:</p>
                  <p>I am <hi>Cloſe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>VVhat mak'ſt thou here?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>I wait upon my charge,</p>
                  <p>I lead your Rival a proceſſion</p>
                  <p>In's ſhirt, perſwading him you had reſolv'd</p>
                  <p>To cut his throat elſe: he's hard by at's prayers,</p>
                  <p>And thinks you have purſu'd him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>Ha! I'll do't:</p>
                  <p>Shew me the fool, by all my hopes I'll kill him,</p>
                  <p>And ſend his baſe heart, as a preſent to her:</p>
                  <p>Fate has preſented me with this revenge,</p>
                  <p>And I will not delay his death a minute.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Indeed, indeed you ſha'not.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>How?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>You dare not.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>My drudge offront me? are you grown his champion?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Not I, ſir, but you dare not do an act</p>
                  <p>So much againſt the honour of a gentleman;</p>
                  <p>You wo'not kill him baſely.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>No.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>VVhy then</p>
                  <p>There is no fear, but he'll live long enough:</p>
                  <p>I'll undertake, he ne'er ſhall grow provided</p>
                  <p>To fight with ye; and other ſatisfaction,</p>
                  <p>Name it and take it; ſo I'll fetch him to you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>Stay, I have been too paſſionate, let him live</p>
                  <p>To be her puniſhment; that's revenge enough</p>
                  <p>While I purſue my own ways.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>VVhither now?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>VVhither you muſt not follow, by thy honeſty:</p>
                  <p>I charge thee come not after me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>That binds my attendance, ſir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>But not when I command the contrary:</p>
                  <p>If thou doſt move this way, thou draw'ſt mine anger:</p>
                  <p>Mind the preſervation of the ſame thing you</p>
                  <p>Undertook: farewel; if thou doſt love me,</p>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:35542:20"/>
                  <p>Follow, not, nor queſtion; 'tis in my power</p>
                  <p>To looſe thee or my ſelf.—</p>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>I cannot ſee i'th' dark with ſpectacles,</p>
                  <p>And mine eyes have loſt him o'the ſudden;</p>
                  <p>VVell, I muſt hope the beſt: what ſhall I do</p>
                  <p>VVith my hen-hearted lover, who would give</p>
                  <p>Half his eſtate, this cold fit were well over?</p>
                  <p>I ſhall make work for the Phyſitians:</p>
                  <p>Caudles and Cullices will not reſtore him;</p>
                  <p>If he but ſcape with life, I am not ſorry:</p>
                  <p>He may be a ſouldier, and endure the trenches;</p>
                  <p>I put him firſt to the becoming ſufferance.</p>
                  <p>But what are theſe? an army of horns and halberts?</p>
                  <p>Upon my conſcience the VVatch: I thought</p>
                  <p>The Fields had not been haunced with theſe goblins:</p>
                  <p>I cannot run; if I ſhould ſquat, and they</p>
                  <p>Find me, there were no mercy but <hi>Bridewel,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Or ſome ſuch louſie place: I am reſolv'd</p>
                  <p>To caſt away a few good words upon 'em;</p>
                  <p>A leg, and worſhipping the Conſtable</p>
                  <p>That leads the ruſty regiment, will quit me;</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> paſs the gates with't often, and ſo may</p>
                  <p>The devil, if he pay the Porter. Bleſs ye</p>
                  <p>My Maſters, what a clock is't?</p>
                  <stage>Enter Conſtable and Watch.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 Watch.</speaker>
                  <p>VVho goes there?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Conſt.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> charge you ſtand.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Your worſhip may do much.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Conſt.</speaker>
                  <p>VVhere have you been?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>At <hi>Iſlington,</hi> an't pleaſe you, about buſineſs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 Watch.</speaker>
                  <p>Some thief <hi>I</hi> warrant him, no honeſt man,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> know by his basket-hilt; ſome rogue that watches:</p>
                  <p>The Fields are peſter'd with ſuch ſturdy robbets.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>He is a rogue that watches, for my part.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Conſt.</speaker>
                  <p>He calls my VVatch-men rogues, perfidious traytor.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 Watch.</speaker>
                  <p>How! Maſter Conſtable,</p>
                  <p>You are one your ſelf</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Conſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Sitrah <hi>I</hi> will teach you to commit felony.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>How, ſir? will you teach me to commit felony? take heed what you ſay, if <hi>I</hi> commit fellony by your authority.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Conſt.</speaker>
                  <p>My tority ſhall ſtretch for't: away with him; if you be not whipt for theſe intergatories, his Majeſty ſhall keep his own peace himſelf; is this a time anight to call honeſt men rogues? away with him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:35542:21"/>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Good ſir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 Watch.</speaker>
                  <p>We will provide you lodging.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Where?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 Watch.</speaker>
                  <p>New priſon.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>But are you in earneſt, gentlemen? for what?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 Watch.</speaker>
                  <p>For anſwering the Conſtable.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Cry him mercy,</p>
                  <p>I ſhew'd him too much manners, if there be</p>
                  <p>No remedy.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 Watch.</speaker>
                  <p>We'll humble you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>I have a</p>
                  <p>Companion hereabouts: where are you, ſir?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Within. Star.</speaker>
                  <p>Here in a ditch.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 Watch.</speaker>
                  <p>They ſeldom go alone,</p>
                  <p>We'll find him out. Ha ſirrah?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Do you hear,</p>
                  <p>You watch about theſe places for no good,</p>
                  <p>It ſeems.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Conſt.</speaker>
                  <p>We watch indeed for knaves.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>You dare not</p>
                  <p>Speak to their faces: ſome of you I am ſure</p>
                  <p>Do watch for your good Maſters o'th' Pariſh.</p>
                  <stage>Enter Startup.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>I thank you honeſt men; where art thou, <hi>Cloſe?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Here: theſe good men will help us to a lodging.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>Bleſſing a'their heart; I am almoſt ſtarv'd.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Conſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, yes, we'll d'ye that favour: come away, ſir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>Where ſhall we go now?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 Watch.</speaker>
                  <p>To priſon.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>How, <hi>Cloſe?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Conſt.</speaker>
                  <p>You ſhall be cloſe enough.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> follow, ſir,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> cannot leave you in adverſity:</p>
                  <p>All this is for your health: clean ſtraw is warm, ſir.</p>
                  <p>You have the benefit of being naked;</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> ſhall have work to morrow in my woollen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Conſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Away, away, bring 'em away.—</p>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Miſtreſs Bellamy and Nurſe.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> heard ſome noiſe, look, call up the ſervants,</p>
                  <p>See if the gentlemen be abed; <hi>I</hi>'m troubled</p>
                  <stage>Exit Nurſe.</stage>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> have not dealt ſo nobly as became me</p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:35542:21"/>
                  <p>With <hi>Hartwel;</hi> and that love which I pretended,</p>
                  <p>If I have drawn his fancy to affect me,</p>
                  <p>Muſt make him ſatisfaction; his language</p>
                  <p>And ſoft demeanor, when he gave me up</p>
                  <p>His reſolution, made me quite forget</p>
                  <p>My purpoſe to have chid him for his levity,</p>
                  <p>So ſoon to leave my daughter, who I know</p>
                  <p>Hath plac'd him neer her heart; and I have done</p>
                  <p>Her injurie, by this tryal of her truth.</p>
                  <stage>Enter Nurſe.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh Miſtreſs!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>What's the matter?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Maſter <hi>Startup</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Is not abed, nor Maſter <hi>Hartwel.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>This is very ſtrange.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>I dare not tell her of his ſhift, they're gone,</p>
                  <p>The doors I found left open, and no ſigne</p>
                  <p>Which way they are beſtowed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>This puzzles me:</p>
                  <p>Pray heaven there be no miſchief in this abſence:</p>
                  <p>Is <hi>Franck</hi> abed?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>What ſhould</p>
                  <p>Move 'em to leave my houſe ſo late? and Maſter <hi>Hartwel</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Without his cloaths? ſome knock; they're there; go ſee.—</p>
                  <stage>Knock. Exit Nurſe.</stage>
                  <p>Beſhrow me but I trembled.</p>
                  <stage>Enter Nurſe.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis a ſtranger,</p>
                  <p>And ſays he would ſpeak with you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>At this late hour?</p>
                  <p>What accidents are theſe? from whence?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>I know not.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>Has he no name? what ſhould this mean?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nurſe.</speaker>
                  <p>He ſays,</p>
                  <p>He is a Country-man of Maſter <hi>Startups.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>Admit him, he perhaps may bring ſome newes.</p>
                  <stage>Enter Country-Gentleman.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coun.</speaker>
                  <p>By your leave Miſtreſs, pardon my importunity</p>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:35542:22"/>
                  <p>At ſo unfit an hour.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>Y'are welcome, ſir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coun.</speaker>
                  <p>I met with fortunate directions,</p>
                  <p>Though I came l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>te: I underſtand you have</p>
                  <p>A gueſt, one <hi>Startup,</hi> of <hi>Northamptonſhire,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That comes a woing to your daughter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>Such</p>
                  <p>A one there was that ſupt with us, and went</p>
                  <p>To bed; but ſince, as I have faith, I know not</p>
                  <p>Which way he has convey'd himſelf: another</p>
                  <p>Gentleman too is miſſing, and his rival.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coun.</speaker>
                  <p>Pray do not mock me, Lady; I have rid</p>
                  <p>A great way, and the buſineſs much concerns him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>You may believe me: he is no ſuch treaſure,</p>
                  <p>I ſhould conceal him.</p>
                  <stage>Enter Frances.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coun.</speaker>
                  <p>Then I ſee you dally;</p>
                  <p>Know, Miſtreſs, you may ſlack your preparations,</p>
                  <p>Your daughter muſt look out another husband;</p>
                  <p>He is contracted.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>How!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coun.</speaker>
                  <p>And ſomething more,</p>
                  <p>Gotten with childe one that without bluſhing</p>
                  <p>I cannot call my daughter; he ſhall make</p>
                  <p>Her credit ſtreight again: although my fortunes</p>
                  <p>Have no equality with his, I ſhall</p>
                  <p>Finde law to force him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>You prefer'd this ſutor:</p>
                  <p>This news returns my blood.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, you ſhall finde</p>
                  <p>All truth I have delivered; I am not ſorry</p>
                  <p>To hear this news; this is no time to ſeek him:</p>
                  <p>Pleaſe you accept the lodging that was his:</p>
                  <p>My ſervant ſhall attend you in the morning,</p>
                  <p>To help you ſearch.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coun.</speaker>
                  <p>You ſeem a noble gentlewoman,</p>
                  <p>I take your courteſie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel. Nurſe,</speaker>
                  <p>a light: pray walk, ſir.—</p>
                  <stage>Exit Coun. and Nurſe.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>I was unkind to <hi>Hartwel,</hi> he not wiſe:</p>
                  <p>But love ſtill apprehends too much or nothing.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel. Frances,</speaker>
                  <p>a word: do you not know what is</p>
                  <p>Become o'theſe Gentlemen?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>Not I, their abſence is ſtrange to me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:35542:22"/>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh <hi>Franck,</hi> I am undone.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>Good heaven forbid.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>This Gentleman, Maſter <hi>Hartwel,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Whom we ſhall never ſee again, I fear.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>How, mother! are you acquainted with any cauſe to fear thus?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis in vain to tell thee how I lov'd him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>Bleſs my ſences! you love him?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>'Bove all the world, affectionately plac'd him</p>
                  <p>Too neer my heart.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>I heard you made pretence</p>
                  <p>Of love, to try him for my ſake; and pardone me</p>
                  <p>If yet I dare not believe more.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh <hi>Franck!</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>My heart doth tremble, I feel coldneſs run</p>
                  <p>Through all my veins.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>I had no other thought</p>
                  <p>At firſt, but wiſely to diſtinguiſh whether</p>
                  <p>His heart was fixt on thee, or my eſtate;</p>
                  <p>With reſolution, if I found him more</p>
                  <p>A courtier of thy fortune, then thy perſon,</p>
                  <p>To puniſh him with loſs of both: but love</p>
                  <p>Hath chang'd the ſcoene and title of our Comedy;</p>
                  <p>And what I meant ſhould ſlip—All his hopes,</p>
                  <p>Hath ruin'd us: his modeſt and calm anſwer,</p>
                  <p>To accept my tender, with ſuch force and reaſon</p>
                  <p>Directed to my fancie, turn'd my purpoſe,</p>
                  <p>And made me his indeed, his perfect lover:</p>
                  <p>But now we have both loſt him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>All the piety</p>
                  <p>That ever taught children to love their mother,</p>
                  <p>Will but ſuffice to keep my heart obedient:</p>
                  <p>Was ever maid ſo miſerable? was there</p>
                  <p>No other in my fate to be my rival?</p>
                  <p>I live too long: Oh break, my poor heart, break;</p>
                  <p>Then ſhe that gave me life, hath took it from me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>Why do you weep?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>I do not weep; or if</p>
                  <p>I do, I know not why.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>Now I perceive,</p>
                  <p>Thy duty was but counterfeit; you love him,</p>
                  <p>Upon my life you love him ſtill: have my</p>
                  <p>Commands no more reſpect? my care and love</p>
                  <p>So ill rewarded? that I deſiring</p>
                  <p>One comfort in the world, and ſhall my childe</p>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:35542:23"/>
                  <p>Riſe up to take that from me?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>Alas, I knew not</p>
                  <p>You lov'd him too; indeed I had rather die</p>
                  <p>Then you ſhould call me rebel: parents often</p>
                  <p>Affect not where their children love; but you</p>
                  <p>With too much loving what my thoughts delight in,</p>
                  <p>Have quite undone your daughter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>Now I ſee</p>
                  <p>The cauſe of his departure in this faſhion:</p>
                  <p>Pray heaven he have not made away himſelf:</p>
                  <p>Did ever childe deceive a mother ſo?</p>
                  <p>I have a ſad preſage: you may to bed,</p>
                  <p>And riſe again without my bleſſing; yet</p>
                  <p>You may ſtay—Wherefore ſhould I deſpair</p>
                  <p>Of his return? you ſay you could not tell</p>
                  <p>That I affected him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>Indeed not I,</p>
                  <p>And do believe it now againſt my will;</p>
                  <p>But I am your daughter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>Shewing it in conforming</p>
                  <p>Your ſelf to my deſires, and what is paſt</p>
                  <p>I can forgive you: if he come again,</p>
                  <p>Will you be rul'd, and ſhew no favour to him?</p>
                  <p>For 'tis in you I ſee to make me happy:</p>
                  <p>I will not tye you to affect th'other:</p>
                  <p>Chuſe any for your husband, but this man,</p>
                  <p>My love and prayers ſhall go along with you.</p>
                  <p>Anſwer.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>Indeed I dare not, yet could I</p>
                  <p>Put off the knowledge that you are my mother.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>What then?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>Though my imagination allow'd you</p>
                  <p>The greateſt Empreſs in the world, whoſe frown</p>
                  <p>Could kill, and eyes at pleaſure make alive</p>
                  <p>Again, thus I could anſwer.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>pray let's hear?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>You do not well to heap oppreſſion:</p>
                  <p>Authority was given to preſerve,</p>
                  <p>Not kill the poor beneath you: I durſt tell you</p>
                  <p>In confidence of my cauſe, that you betray</p>
                  <p>Two innocents to ſorrow; and though heaven</p>
                  <p>Look on, and ſeem to ſmile upon your cruelty,</p>
                  <p>Yet there is thunder, for divorcing thoſe,</p>
                  <p>Whoſe hearts That hath conjoyn'd: I durſt ſay more,</p>
                  <p>Though all your terrors were prepar'd to puniſh</p>
                  <p>My bold defence, and call you tyrant.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:35542:23"/>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>How?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>A moſt unjuſt, a ſacrilegious tyrant.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>You would not be ſo violent.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>That do</p>
                  <p>Not onely ruine and deface the altar,</p>
                  <p>But ſteal away the very ſacrifice:</p>
                  <p>And I durſt adde, and ſmile upon your anger,</p>
                  <p>Though as you frown'd, death lurk'd in every wrinkle,</p>
                  <p>My ſoul's above your tyranny; and would</p>
                  <p>From torturing flames receive new fire of love,</p>
                  <p>And make your eye faint to behold the brightneſs</p>
                  <p>Of my poor bodies Martyrdome; and if ever</p>
                  <p>Love ſhew'd a miracle, my heart ſhould bear</p>
                  <p>The characters of him you have torn from it,</p>
                  <p>With beams about it like a Saint that ſuffer'd.</p>
                  <p>But as you are my mother, thus I kneel,</p>
                  <p>And beg a pardon for my innocence;</p>
                  <p>If that offend you, live you happy ſtill,</p>
                  <p>And be the Miſtreſs of your vows: live to</p>
                  <p>Enjoy whom you affect; may every hour</p>
                  <p>Return new bleſſings on you both; renew</p>
                  <p>Your ſpring, and let him think you young again;</p>
                  <p>And let me beg but this for all my duty,</p>
                  <p>Againſt the day you marry him, to provide</p>
                  <p>My coſfin; for <hi>I</hi> fear, <hi>I</hi> ſha'not have</p>
                  <p>Breath many minutes after, to pray for you:</p>
                  <p>The herbs that ſhall adorn your bridal chamber,</p>
                  <p>Will ſerve my funeral, and deck my hearſe:</p>
                  <p>Beneath which you ſhall ſay, There lies your daughter</p>
                  <p>That dy'd to ſhew obedience.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>Why ſhouldſt thou</p>
                  <p>Continue thus to him?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> know he loves me</p>
                  <p>Still, though hereafter your affections</p>
                  <p>May meet.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>And they ſhall meet,</p>
                  <p>But never to procure thee one bad thought:</p>
                  <p>Now <hi>I</hi> have tryed you both, aſſure my child</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> lov'd him but for thee; diſpoſe thy ſelf</p>
                  <p>To be his bride; this news at his return</p>
                  <p>VVill make all well:—To reſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>Can this be true?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>'Twere ſin to mock thee any more—To bed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>No, <hi>I</hi>'ll ſpend all this night in prayers for you,</p>
                  <p>My deareſt mother: Oh my <hi>Hartwel!</hi>—</p>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:35542:24"/>Enter Playfaire, and the Doctor his Brother.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Doct.</speaker>
                  <p>How like you her now?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>The morning never bloom'd</p>
                  <p>So freſh, nor <hi>Venus</hi> with more charms upon her:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Adon</hi> would melt before her eye, and woo</p>
                  <p>Her kiſſes at the expence of her laſt breath:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cupid</hi> himſelf, could he but ſee, would fall</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In</hi> love with her, and throwing away his ſhafts,</p>
                  <p>Offer the empty quiver to her eyes,</p>
                  <p>Ambitious to fill it with her beams,</p>
                  <p>The leaſt of which would wound more hearts, then all</p>
                  <p>His ſtock of golden arrows.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Doct.</speaker>
                  <p>No more raptures.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>Didſt thou not know before, that love is able</p>
                  <p>VVithout the help of ſack to make a poet?</p>
                  <p>My nimble <hi>Mercury; Joves</hi> Herald in</p>
                  <p>Reverſion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Doct.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> confeſs,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> had a trick of <hi>Mercury,</hi> when <hi>I</hi> pick'd</p>
                  <p>His pocket for the keys.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>He never miſt 'em.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Doct.</speaker>
                  <p>His eyes were drench'd in ſuds, and we return'd 'em</p>
                  <p>Ere they recover'd light.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>'Twas excellent,</p>
                  <p>He was in darkneſs ſtill.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Doct.</speaker>
                  <p>D'ye think he'll know her?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>His cloaths already have.</p>
                  <p>Made him forget himſelf; or if he have</p>
                  <p>But the remembrance of ſuch a woman,</p>
                  <p>The more he ſees her now, the more he'll think</p>
                  <p>The change impoſſible.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Doct.</speaker>
                  <p>VVhere have you left him?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>I'th' Gallery, where with much patience,</p>
                  <p>He does expect his Highneſs will ſend for him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Doct.</speaker>
                  <p>Then all runs ſmooth, his wonder does continue.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> fed that humour artificially,</p>
                  <p>He is half perſwaded all is but a dream yet:</p>
                  <p>To which imagination, his cloaths</p>
                  <p>Are a great help, becauſe he paid not for 'em:</p>
                  <p>Sometimes he is very merry, then again</p>
                  <p>He ſtruts about with ſuch a ſcurvie pride,</p>
                  <p>As ſome new crept into nobility,</p>
                  <p>VVhen ſome of their firſt livery come to ſee 'em.</p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:35542:24"/>
                  <p>His honour has ſo chang'd him, that he now</p>
                  <p>Knows not of what religion he is;</p>
                  <p>Or if by chance he thinks of his firſt faith,</p>
                  <p>He ſpits o'th' hangings, and excuſes with</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> do not like the ſtory, 'tis apocryphal:</p>
                  <p>Sometimes he'll offer at a jeſt,</p>
                  <p>Frown upon any man that will preſume</p>
                  <p>To have more knowledge in worſe cloaths: I told him</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi>t was his Graces pleaſure he ſhould be</p>
                  <p>Controuler at the Mask, and he did ſweat</p>
                  <p>As he were ſtudying for ſome mighty oaths</p>
                  <p>To clear the preſence.—He is here, away—</p>
                  <stage>Exit Doctor and Playfaire.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Hornet and Poldavis.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Are you the Maſter of the houſe, ſir <hi>Poldavis?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> heard you call'd.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi>t is my name,</p>
                  <p>Sir <hi>Gyles,</hi> unworthy of this Grace his Highneſs</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi>s daign'd to ſhew in honouring of my daughter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>And was ſhe married this morning, ſay you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
                  <p>This morn ſhe loſt her Virgin-Name.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> have</p>
                  <p>Not ſeen her yot, nor any of the Ladies;</p>
                  <p>You have but little noiſe methinks i'th' houſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi>t would offend his Grace.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>VVho as you ſay</p>
                  <p>Came hither privately, with a ſmall train</p>
                  <p>Of Lords: would <hi>I</hi> might ſee his face again:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> am not ſent for yet; I have been ready,</p>
                  <p>Sir <hi>Pol</hi>—theſe three hours; and <hi>I</hi> do wonder</p>
                  <p>His Grace ſo much forgets himſelf.</p>
                  <stage>Flouriſh.</stage>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pol.</hi> That muſick</p>
                  <p>Speaks him on entrance.</p>
                  <stage>Enter Lambert, Playfaire and attendance.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I,</hi> this garb becomes him;</p>
                  <p>How was his perſon loſt within that ſhape</p>
                  <p>He was firſt preſented to me!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Indeed the caſe</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi>s ſomething altered, by your Highneſs bounty,</p>
                  <p>To your poor ſervant <hi>Hornet.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>How he looks</p>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:35542:25"/>
                  <p>As he did ſcorn the Quorum, and were hungry</p>
                  <p>To eat a States-man! 'las an office in</p>
                  <p>The houſhold is too little for a breakfaſt,</p>
                  <p>A Baron but a mornings draught, he'll gulp it</p>
                  <p>Like a round egge in Muſcadine; methinks</p>
                  <p>At every wiping of his mouth, ſhould drop</p>
                  <p>A golden ſaying of <hi>Pythagoras:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A piece of <hi>Matchiavel</hi> I ſee already</p>
                  <p>Hang on his beard, which wants but ſtroking out;</p>
                  <p>The ſtatutes and the <hi>Magna Charta</hi> have</p>
                  <p>Taken a Leaſe at his tongues end.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                  <p>We'll think on't; he ſhall be—But</p>
                  <p>To the banquet: Then let the Mask be ready,</p>
                  <p>There we ſhall employ your worthy diligence.—</p>
                  <stage>Flouriſh.</stage>
                  <stage>Exit Lambert and attendance.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Heaven bleſs your mighty Grace.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>You'll follow.—</p>
                  <stage>Exit Playfaire.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>I attend you preſently:</p>
                  <p>I know not what to think of theſe things yet;</p>
                  <p>'Tis very ſtrange I ſhould be thus exalted,</p>
                  <p>Without deſert, beſt known unto my ſelf:</p>
                  <p>Princes I ſee are mortal, and may be</p>
                  <p>Deceived in placing of their honours: I</p>
                  <p>Am little better then a favorite,</p>
                  <p>If theſe be true, if theſe be true; 'tis a queſtion,</p>
                  <p>Let me conſider wiſely; it may be</p>
                  <p>I am not I, not <hi>Hornet,</hi> no, I'm a Knight:</p>
                  <p>Are theſe my cloaths? I do not uſe to wear ſuch:</p>
                  <p>A pocket in my ſleeve, and velvet hoſe,</p>
                  <p>Six times tranſlated ſince they were a Midwifes</p>
                  <p>Forepart, were things I wore on holydays:</p>
                  <p>The price of theſe would break a Camels back;</p>
                  <p>And yet ſome men walk under them like Elephants,</p>
                  <p>And have variety as the devil were</p>
                  <p>Their Taylour; who beſt knows where all their land lies:</p>
                  <p>Then why this coſt on me?—'Tis a dream;</p>
                  <p>I am now confirm'd, a very idle dream,</p>
                  <p>And I am very glad on't: 'tis impoſſible</p>
                  <p>It ſhould be true, it does not hang together:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> will have paience, till I wake again,</p>
                  <p>And care not what becomes on't.</p>
                  <stage>Enter Playfaires brother for the 4 Lord.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>4 Lord.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis his highneſs pleaſure,</p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:35542:25"/>
                  <p>Now the banquet's done.—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>How, the banquet done! I was coming to't'</p>
                  <p>You could hardly ſay grace by this time.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>4 Lord.</speaker>
                  <p>That's a ceremony</p>
                  <p>Grown out of uſe; it was a running banquet.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>A running! ſo it ſeems, it was a galloping banquet,</p>
                  <p>For you made haſte: I do dream certainly,</p>
                  <p>There's no ſence nor reaſon in any thing they do.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>4 Lord.</speaker>
                  <p>You know your place,</p>
                  <p>The Mask will ſtreight begin; and his Grace will not</p>
                  <p>Have any one admitted: he reſolves,</p>
                  <p>If the conceipt affects him, it ſhall be</p>
                  <p>Perform'd at Court hereafter: i'th' mean time</p>
                  <p>He does command all privacie; they are</p>
                  <p>Some ſet to guard the door, but your care muſt</p>
                  <p>Provide his Highneſs be not interrupted:</p>
                  <p>Hark, they are rude already—</p>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Let me alone:</p>
                  <p>What turbulent knave is that?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Within.</speaker>
                  <p>I am a Country-Gentleman, ſir <hi>Gyles;</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And if I may preſume upon good cloaths,</p>
                  <p>You may before his Grace call me your Cozen,</p>
                  <p>And not be aſham'd: here is a Lady too.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>A Lady too? is ſhe with child? what makes ſhe</p>
                  <p>Here, and ſhe be with child already? I</p>
                  <p>Tell thee, none ſuch ſhall be admitted while</p>
                  <p>I am in place—More rapping?—Keep the doors,</p>
                  <p>If I do fall a ſwearing once, look to't.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Within.</speaker>
                  <p>I beſeech you for my wives ſake.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Thy wives?</p>
                  <p>What's he that pleads in <hi>forma pauperis?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Within.</speaker>
                  <p>A Citizen, and like me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Like me? thou lieſt, I am more like a Lord,</p>
                  <p>Thou ſha't fare ne'er the better for that word:</p>
                  <p>Knock down the women, if there be a hundred,</p>
                  <p>And make their husbands drunk, the guard are lazie:</p>
                  <p>Theſe womens inſolence will force a ſtatute:</p>
                  <p>I will petition to the Prince my ſelf,</p>
                  <p>They may have liberty but once a year</p>
                  <p>To ſee the galliefoyſt, then be conſin'd</p>
                  <p>To their chamber and one 'Prentiſe—Yet again?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Within.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir <hi>Gyles,</hi> ſir <hi>Gyles,</hi> you know me well enough.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>But while I am in office, I know no body.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Within.</speaker>
                  <p>I am your Scrivener.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Draw the purſe wherein</p>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:35542:26"/>
                  <p>Thou keptſt thy ears, and leave 'em at the door,</p>
                  <p>The guard truſts none without a pawn; they'll ſerve</p>
                  <p>If they be ne'er redeem'd, to ſeeth in milk</p>
                  <p>For a ſore throat.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Within.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir <hi>Gyles,</hi> here is your Neece.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>My Neece! the devil ſhe is.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neece.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>VVithin.</hi> Pray Unckle let me in.</p>
                  <stage>Enter Servant.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Her very voice—Ha, open the doors there:</p>
                  <p>Where is ſhe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <p>Whom?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>My Neece that call'd me?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <p>None call'd, nor was there any women here.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>No, nor my Scrivener, hawling out ſir <hi>Gyles?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <p>Not any nam'd your worſhip.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Then I dream,</p>
                  <p>And I am a fool to make a queſtion on't.—</p>
                  <stage>Exit Servant.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>VVithin.</speaker>
                  <p>Ha, ha, ha.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>The Knaves laugh at me too; but let 'em: I</p>
                  <p>Shall be as merry with this tale to morrow.</p>
                  <stage>Flouriſh.</stage>
                  <p>What fancies men have in their ſleep ſometimes!</p>
                  <p>His Highneſs! where be the Ladies?</p>
                  <stage>Enter Lambert, Poldavis and atttendants.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
                  <p>They are all i'th' Mask.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, no matter where; why do I ask the queſtion?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
                  <p>You'll ſee them, ſir, anon.</p>
                  <stage>Poldavis gives papers to Lambert and ſir Gyles.</stage>
                  <p>Wilt pleaſe your Grace,</p>
                  <p>And you, ſir <hi>Gyles,</hi> the ſubject of the Mask?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>What's here? <hi>The three Goddeſſes Contention for the Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Ball.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <stage>Dance.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Playfaire in his own apparel: He dances with a golden Ball in his hand.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>This is <hi>Paris,</hi> ha! I have ſeen that fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e before now.</p>
                  <stage>Enter Juno, Pallas and Venus.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Theſe are the three Goddeſſes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Juno, Pallas</hi> and <hi>Venus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <stage>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:35542:26"/>The Goddeſſes dance, and court Paris for his Ball: To Juno enters one like a King; She takes off his Crown, and offereth it to Paris: he aceepts not.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Juno</hi> doth woo him with her State and Kingdom.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                  <p>But he refuſes.</p>
                  <stage>To Pallas enters one like a Souldier, plum'd and rich: She preſents him to Paris, with a book; he refuſes.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                  <p>He is not for her ſervice, though ſhe offer</p>
                  <p>To make him Scholar and a Souldier,</p>
                  <p>A compleat man.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>That Fairy wins the Ball.</p>
                  <stage>To Venus comes Cupid, leading in Hornets Neece, richly dreſt.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Ha! that is my Neece.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
                  <p>Which, ſir <hi>Gyles?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>That Lady whom Dame <hi>Venus</hi> and her brat are buſie withal.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
                  <p>Contain your ſelf, ſir <hi>Gyles,</hi> that is the Bride.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>The Bride quotha!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
                  <p>Married this morning.</p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Paris gives Venus the Ball: Juno, Pallas, King and Souldier.</hi>—Exeunt Maskquers.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Theſe are my keys; ſhe's ſafe enough at home,</p>
                  <p>And has but half her wits, as I remember:</p>
                  <p>The devil cannot juggle her from my cuſtody: Ha, ha,</p>
                  <p>I do dream ſtill.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis time to break off ſports: how like you this,</p>
                  <p>Sir <hi>Gyles?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>A very pretty dream.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſee you wo'd be abed, you are not us'd to ſuch late hours.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
                  <p>Lights for his Highneſs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>I humbly beg your licence,</p>
                  <p>I may return to my old lodging.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:35542:27"/>Lam.</speaker>
                  <p>Well ſir, 'tis eaſily granted.—</p>
                  <stage>Flouriſh.</stage>
                  <stage>Exit Lambert and attendants.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
                  <p>Lights for ſir <hi>Gyles,</hi> one ſhall attend you home.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Ha, ha, ha.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pol.</speaker>
                  <p>Why do you laugh?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>At a conceipt, at a conceipt:</p>
                  <p>What did I eat laſt night, to make me dream thus?—</p>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </sp>
               <trailer>Finis Actus Quartus.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="act">
               <head>Actus Quintus.</head>
               <stage>Enter Hartwel, Country-Gentleman, Servant and Officers.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>YOu have done well.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coun.</speaker>
                  <p>VVwould you had done no worſe:</p>
                  <p>Theſe are his cloaths, and you muſt give account</p>
                  <p>How you came by 'em, and produce him ſafe,</p>
                  <p>Ere you acquit your ſelf: we may ſuſpect</p>
                  <p>You have kill'd him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>Then I obey my deſtiny:</p>
                  <p>Juſtice will ſtill purſue the guilty perſon;</p>
                  <p>Diſpoſe me where you pleaſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <p>He does confeſs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>What ere you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, you can but have my life</p>
                  <p>For his, all your revenge can reach no higher,</p>
                  <p>And to the law <hi>I</hi> yeild my ſelf.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coun.</speaker>
                  <p>My hopes are</p>
                  <p>Cold as his blood whom thou haſt ſlain: thou haſt</p>
                  <p>Been cruel in this act, to me and mine,</p>
                  <p>VVhoſe fames in him are miſerably wounded;</p>
                  <p>But look for the reward.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>I muſt expect it:</p>
                  <p>In the mean time, I wo'not beg your mercy;</p>
                  <p>Life is a burden I would fain be rid of,</p>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:35542:27"/>
                  <p>Does weary me to carry it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <p>I'll acquaint</p>
                  <p>My Miſtreſs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coun.</speaker>
                  <p>Do ſo: to the next juſtice with him,</p>
                  <p>Come away.—</p>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Hornet.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>She's gone; ſhe's gone, I ſhall run mad: my Neece,</p>
                  <p>Rob'd of three thouſand pounds in her eſcape,</p>
                  <p>And yet the doors were ſafe: ſome witch has taught her,</p>
                  <p>Or ſome French boy, to clime a chimney; elſe</p>
                  <p>I cannot think which way ſhe is convey'd:</p>
                  <p>I find too late, I am awake and gul'd,</p>
                  <p>Nor know I whom to accuſe for my tormentors,</p>
                  <p>Devils or men; but ſure they were not men,</p>
                  <p>But very fiends I revell'd with laſt night:</p>
                  <p>Though mortals want no malice, they have not art</p>
                  <p>To undo me of this faſhion: Oh that I</p>
                  <p>Knew where to meet the prince of devils knighted me;</p>
                  <p>The Poets call him <hi>Pluto,</hi> god of riches;</p>
                  <p>I and my learned counſel would undo him</p>
                  <p>In law, in very law, which he ſhould find</p>
                  <p>Hotter ere I had done, then hell it ſelf,</p>
                  <p>And call his place of torments in three terms,</p>
                  <p>But a refreſhing to't: yet let me ſee,</p>
                  <p>I have her portion ſtill, though ſhe be vaniſht;</p>
                  <p>That's better then my Neece; but if ſhe marry,</p>
                  <p>I looſe it all; there, there is the vexation.</p>
                  <stage>Enter Lambert.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                  <p>Save Maſter <hi>Hornet.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis too late, away,</p>
                  <p>I do not love unneceſſary complement.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                  <p>This he?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes I am he, am I not very fine?</p>
                  <p>What do you think this trim will coſt me? ha!</p>
                  <p>Three thouſand pound, no more.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                  <p>The broker wo'not</p>
                  <p>Lend half the mony.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Will you, ſir, be gone?</p>
                  <p>I have no money to lend now; it is not</p>
                  <p>You know in faſhion, with rich cloaths.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                  <p>I am</p>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:35542:28"/>
                  <p>For other purpoſe, and with news perhaps</p>
                  <p>You would be willing to receive; you have</p>
                  <p>A Neece.—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor,</speaker>
                  <p>No, ſuch a creature was in my poſſeſſion:</p>
                  <p>Do you know where ſhe is?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                  <p>I imagine.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Ha! good Maſter <hi>Lambert,</hi> on, pray forward;</p>
                  <p>You ſhall have mony upon good ſecurity.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                  <p>I think you ſir, for nothing; I owe you</p>
                  <p>Too much already, on theſe terms.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>My Neece,</p>
                  <p>As you were ſaying.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                  <p>Were you knighted lately?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Ha! is that talk abroad?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                  <p>No general rumour; by a chance I came</p>
                  <p>Where ſuch a thing was whiſper'd, only whiſper'd,</p>
                  <p>Juſt as he was deſcrib'd: in my opinion</p>
                  <p>Y'are very hanſome, and do look as like.—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>An aſs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                  <p>VVhy you ſhall have it, ſir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>But touching</p>
                  <p>My Neece, good ſir, that moſt ungratious giglot,</p>
                  <p>That's run or ſtolen away, juggled laſt night</p>
                  <p>Out of my doors.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                  <p>Did ſhe not leap the Caſement?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Do not encreaſe my agonie, you came.—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                  <p>With civil meaning to diſcover how</p>
                  <p>You may be abus'd.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>VVhat mony do you want, ſir?</p>
                  <p>Your own bond ſhall ſuffice.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                  <p>I have forſworn</p>
                  <p>Writing my name, or mark; but I can tell you.—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Where I may finde this Girl?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                  <p>More I can do,</p>
                  <p>If need require; 'tis in my power to give</p>
                  <p>Her back to your poſſeſſion, and I am willing.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>An honeſt man.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                  <p>On reaſonable conditions,</p>
                  <p>And ſuch as ſhall not trench on borrowing mony.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Honeſter yet.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                  <p>For you ſhall give it freely, and get by it:</p>
                  <p>Sir, you muſt underſtand, if I do this,</p>
                  <p>I ſhall betray a friend of mine, that has</p>
                  <p>Put me in truſt; one that intends to marry her,</p>
                  <p>D'ye mark? and get three thouſand pound upon her;</p>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:35542:28"/>
                  <p>One that has lent me ſums too, without parchment,</p>
                  <p>Or fooliſh circumſtance to be return'd;</p>
                  <p>VVhich you were never yet ſo much a Chriſtian,</p>
                  <p>As to be guilty of, in your Uſurers Gallon</p>
                  <p>Of Conſcience-melting Sack: this deſerves ſomething,</p>
                  <p>'Tis part of my revenew: younger brothers</p>
                  <p>Are glad of penſion; it helps to tooke</p>
                  <p>At Ordinaries, and pay trifling reckonings, that</p>
                  <p>Ariſe to a bill or tedious circumſtance</p>
                  <p>Of cleer Orphographie, for Cock and Mallard,</p>
                  <p>VVhich puts the Bar-boy to Arithmetick,</p>
                  <p>Becauſe ſome expedition is required;</p>
                  <p>You have a bond of mine.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>For fifty pounds.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                  <p>I had but forty, and the Scrivener paid;</p>
                  <p>VVith whom your worſhip too perhaps divided:</p>
                  <p>If you remember, there were pretious dinners,</p>
                  <p>Ere I could count the chickens all together;</p>
                  <p>Which was your thrift and my expence: you ſhall</p>
                  <p>Firſt cancel that bond; nay this wo'not do't,</p>
                  <p>And give, d'ye mark? give me a hundred pieces,</p>
                  <p>Perhaps I'll drink your health; this ſhall betray</p>
                  <p>Your Neece again, give her into your hands,</p>
                  <p>Though for my treachery I be ſung in ballads,</p>
                  <p>And have the Town-curſe, if I ever marry,</p>
                  <p>To ſhew my wife can graft well.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis too much,</p>
                  <p>For no more labour, ſir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                  <p>If you conſider,</p>
                  <p>Two hundred will not bring me to't again:</p>
                  <p>Thus fair I'll deal with ye, I'll not have a croſs</p>
                  <p>Till I have don't, but then I will be ſure on't:</p>
                  <p>Fetch, fetch the buſineſs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>The bond is ready.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                  <p>I will have ready mony too, you have</p>
                  <p>Bags of all ſizes, and denominations;</p>
                  <p>Thoſe things do promiſe well,</p>
                  <p>Now I attend you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Do this feat for me, and 'tis all thine own.—</p>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Juſtice, Playfaire, his Brother, Neece.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Juſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Now we may wiſh you joy, the Prieſt hath tyed</p>
                  <p>That knot, no ſubtlety nor malice can</p>
                  <p>Diſſolve; and I repent not I have been</p>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:35542:29"/>
                  <p>An actor in your Comedy; though I ſhould not</p>
                  <p>Be temped eaſily to ſuch another</p>
                  <p>Engagement: for your ſake, I have diſpenc'd with</p>
                  <p>My perſon and my place</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play</speaker>
                  <p>You were always</p>
                  <p>My loving Unkle.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neece.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, you have in this</p>
                  <p>Deſerv'd our lives and fortunes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bro.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> have plaid</p>
                  <p>My part too.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou haſt ſhewed thy ſelf a Doctor,</p>
                  <p>VVhich ſhall be a happy <hi>Omen</hi> to thy ſtudies.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bro.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> have ſhew'd my ſelf a Brother, ſir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neece.</speaker>
                  <p>That name</p>
                  <p>I muſt know often too.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bro.</speaker>
                  <p>Moſt happy in</p>
                  <p>A vertuous Siſter, I congratulate</p>
                  <p>Again your wiſh'd enlargement, and the meeting</p>
                  <p>Of both your loving hearts.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>It was good mirth,</p>
                  <p>To hear him confident all our device</p>
                  <p>VVas but a dream.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Juſt.</speaker>
                  <p>He is awake by this time,</p>
                  <p>Should <hi>Lambert</hi> fail, we'll have another way</p>
                  <p>To invite him; and if honeſtie prevail not,</p>
                  <p>Force ſhame, till he conſent.</p>
                  <stage>Enter Servant.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <p>Some offenders, ſir,</p>
                  <p>Are brought to be examined.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Juſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Nephew, withdraw, with your fair Bride; theſe troubles</p>
                  <p>Are incident to my place, <hi>I</hi>'ll ſoon diſpatch 'em.—</p>
                  <stage>Exit Playfaire, Brother, Neece and Servant.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Hartwel, Country-Gentleman and Officers.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Juſt.</speaker>
                  <p>How now, my Maſters; Maſter <hi>Hartwel?</hi> ha!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Har.</speaker>
                  <p>Look on me, ſir, as a delinquent: theſe</p>
                  <p>Are able to accuſe me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Juſt.</speaker>
                  <p>VVhat's his offence?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coun.</speaker>
                  <p>Nothing but killing of a man.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Juſt.</speaker>
                  <p>VVhat proof?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coun.</speaker>
                  <p>He has confeſt it, ſir.</p>
                  <stage>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:35542:29"/>Enter Miſtreſs Bellamy and Frances.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Juſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Miſtreſs <hi>Bellamy,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Y'are come in a ſad time; here's Maſter <hi>Hartwel</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Accus'd for killing.—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis not poſſible:</p>
                  <p>Good ſir, believe it not.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Juſt.</speaker>
                  <p>He does confeſs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>I am not worth your pity, gentle Lady:</p>
                  <p>In vain <hi>I</hi> ſhould extenuate my fact,</p>
                  <p>To ſave the trouble of examinations;</p>
                  <p>Here I confeſs again my hand is guilty</p>
                  <p>Of killing him, whoſe feeble arm durſt not</p>
                  <p>Lift up a weapon to defend himſelf.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Juſt.</speaker>
                  <p>That was not manly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>I but ſlew a coward ſo,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Startup;</hi> and could <hi>I</hi> call his life again,</p>
                  <p>I ſhould as ſoon deſtroy it; you perhaps</p>
                  <p>Know not my provocations; he was</p>
                  <p>My Rival, ſir: pardon me, Miſtreſs <hi>Bellamy,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To whom I only ſeem'd a proſelyte</p>
                  <p>In love: I had no heart to give from her;</p>
                  <p>And in my ſtudy to decline your anger,</p>
                  <p>I fell upon her ſcorn; which in a few minutes</p>
                  <p>Engag'd me to this fate: nor am I troubled,</p>
                  <p>That I muſt die; when ſhe upon whoſe faith</p>
                  <p>I durſt have laid the hopes of my eternity,</p>
                  <p>Hath violated all the truſt of woman.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coun.</speaker>
                  <p>Will't pleaſe you, ſir?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Juſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Forbear a little.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>Tell me, thou moſt unkind, if thou didſt love</p>
                  <p>At all; how couldſt thou think I could be ſuch</p>
                  <p>A deſperate Atheiſt, that thou ſo ſoon,</p>
                  <p>With ſo ſtrange Apoſtacie, ſhould'ſt revenge it?</p>
                  <p>Theſe ſwelling drops, which in thy innocence</p>
                  <p>Might have prevail'd to have reſtor'd the dead,</p>
                  <p>Heaven now doth look on, and deſpiſe; and though</p>
                  <p>Thou ſhed moiſt tribute on this tomb,'t ſhall ſlide</p>
                  <p>Neglected on the marble, and be loſt;</p>
                  <p>As if the ſtone had ſence, to puniſh thy</p>
                  <p>Diſdain of me; I can behold thee weeping,</p>
                  <p>And not be mov'd to wiſh I were not guilty</p>
                  <p>Of killing him, whoſe love had been thy tryumph;</p>
                  <p>And I dare boldly ſtill ſtand in the contempt</p>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:35542:30"/>
                  <p>Of what I am to ſuffer, and the juſtice</p>
                  <p>Of my own truth; challenge thy ſoul to anſwer,</p>
                  <p>In what I was beneath that gaudy fool,</p>
                  <p>Excepting that he had more earth then I</p>
                  <p>To help his ſcale, which yet he may be in debt for</p>
                  <p>To his fathers ſins; alive he could not merit</p>
                  <p>One cold diſdain from thee; and dead, how comes it</p>
                  <p>He ſhould be worth thy tears? but let thy eyes</p>
                  <p>Chide this unruly ſorrow: dreſs thy cheeks</p>
                  <p>With thy freſh blood again, and let thy face</p>
                  <p>Open a book of ſmiles, in the aſſurance</p>
                  <p>I have not long to live: when I have numbred</p>
                  <p>A few ſad minutes, thou ſha't be reveng'd,</p>
                  <p>And I ſhall never trouble thee; if this</p>
                  <p>Be not enough, extend thy malice further,</p>
                  <p>And if thou find'ſt one man that lov'd me living.</p>
                  <p>Will honour this cold body with a grave,</p>
                  <p>Be cruel, and corrupt his charity:</p>
                  <p>So fare you well.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>Yet you muſt ſtay and hear me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>He ſha'not ſuffer, if my friends or ſtate</p>
                  <p>Can purchaſe him a pardon: where's the body</p>
                  <p>Of him that's ſlain?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coun.</speaker>
                  <p>We know not, here is all</p>
                  <p>The free confeſſion of the fact.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>This may</p>
                  <p>Proceed from diſcontents: life to ſome men</p>
                  <p>Is but their torment, in whoſe pain they will</p>
                  <p>As on the rack, often confeſs what never</p>
                  <p>VVas in their thought.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>Speak it again, and I</p>
                  <p>Dare promiſe thee to live.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <p>My heart was ever</p>
                  <p>Conſtant, my mothers love was but thy tryal,</p>
                  <p>As mine, a ſeeming change in thy diſguiſe,</p>
                  <p>Applied by thy too tender apprehenſion;</p>
                  <p>The words were, I would chuſe my husband here:</p>
                  <p>But what will this avail us?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>Maſter Juſtice, I here diſcharge you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Juſt.</speaker>
                  <p>How!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>My joy obeys</p>
                  <p>No limits, I accus'd my ſelf unjuſtly:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Startup</hi>'s alive.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Juſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Where?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay I know not that:</p>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:35542:30"/>
                  <p>My ſervant's with him; but if he have plaid</p>
                  <p>The hangman, ſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y'd or ſmother'd him in a ditch,</p>
                  <p>I have made fair work.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>This wore a welcome truth.</p>
                  <stage>Enter Servant.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, the Conſtable.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Juſt.</speaker>
                  <p>I had rather it had been <hi>Lambert</hi> and the Uſurer.</p>
                  <p>But wait, and give me knowledge when they come.—</p>
                  <stage>Exit Servant.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Conſtable, Cloſe, Startup, Officers.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Conſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Where's Maſter Juſtice?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>Ha! 'tis he and <hi>Cloſe,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Then I am ſecure, your pardon and thy love.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>You have it freely, and a mothers prayers</p>
                  <p>For both your happineſs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Conſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Pleaſe your worſhip, I have brought before you two vagrants that we took laſt night i'th' field, between one and two a clock in the morning; very ſuſpicious vagrants; and by my own authority, I condemn'd 'em becauſe it was late.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>Shall we be hang'd, <hi>Cloſe?</hi> we are condemn'd already.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Conſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Coming this morning to the priſon, I found them drinking away ſorrow in double juggs, to the very ſtaggering of my authority: I beſeech your worſhip to draw a pair of Mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens for 'em both; for they deſerve to be made ſamplers, and whipt for the edification of the Common-wealth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>This is the Gentleman was kill'd, ſir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>No, ſir,</p>
                  <p>Not kill'd outright, but I was almoſt ſtarv'd</p>
                  <p>With cold; theſe Gentlewomen know me,</p>
                  <p>And I ſhould know that hoſe and doublet;</p>
                  <p>Thoſe garments that you wear, I oft have ſeen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>Well ſaid <hi>Jeronymo.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>I was fain to borrow</p>
                  <p>Theſe of a priſoner, that lies in upon</p>
                  <p>A diamond.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Juſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Officers you are diſcharg'd—</p>
                  <stage>Exit Officers.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>And we too?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Juſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, and joy in every boſom.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cloſe,</hi> you muſt know this Miſtreſs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>How!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>My wife, ſir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:35542:31"/>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>It is enough for you to know her, ſir,</p>
                  <p>And me to acknowledge.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coun.</speaker>
                  <p>D'ye know me, ſir?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, and your daughter too:</p>
                  <p>Who brought you to town?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Coun.</speaker>
                  <p>And you ſhall right her.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Star.</speaker>
                  <p>Is ſhe grown crooked? pox on her, I know too well:</p>
                  <p>Peace, not a word more, I know your meaning,</p>
                  <p>Do not diſcredit me, and we'll ſteal down</p>
                  <p>And marry her, ere any be aware on't:</p>
                  <p>I wo'not ſtay to ſhift me, take no leave:</p>
                  <p>The jeſt will be, when I am in the Country,</p>
                  <p>How like an Aſs he'll look on my apparel.—</p>
                  <stage>Exit Startup and Coun.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Servant.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, Maſter <hi>Lambert,</hi> and if I be not</p>
                  <p>Miſtaken, the Uſurer <hi>Hornet</hi> very gallant.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Juſt.</speaker>
                  <p>I muſt entreat your patience a while;</p>
                  <p>You'll meet with friends i'the next room.—</p>
                  <stage>Exeunt: manet Juſtice.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Lambert and Hornet.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                  <p>Excuſe</p>
                  <p>Our boldneſs, ſir, this gentleman.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Juſt.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſhould know him:</p>
                  <p>Maſter <hi>Hornet,</hi> you are very welcome.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Good ſir,</p>
                  <p>No ceremony, we are come to you</p>
                  <p>'Bout buſineſs: I have loſt my Neece, and would</p>
                  <p>Know where ſhe is.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Juſt.</speaker>
                  <p>D'ye take me for a Wizzard?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                  <p>With your favour, our deſires are that you would</p>
                  <p>Be witneſs to a bargain, and receive</p>
                  <p>Some trifles, ſir, in truſt to be delivered</p>
                  <p>To me, if I reſtore his kinſwoman.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Not elſe, on that condition I depoſite</p>
                  <p>Theſe hundred pieces and a bond; if he</p>
                  <p>Deliver me my Neece, they are his fraught;</p>
                  <p>If not, they call me owner.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                  <p>Pardon, ſir,</p>
                  <p>That I preſume to bring this trouble to ye.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Juſt.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis none at all.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:35542:31"/>Lam.</speaker>
                  <p>You ſha'not expect long;</p>
                  <p>So reſt you merry.—</p>
                  <stage>Exit Lambert.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Juſt.</speaker>
                  <p>How fare you, ſir?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>As you ſee, faln away an inch ſince morning;</p>
                  <p>But this will phyſick me: if I poſſeſs</p>
                  <p>This harlotry again, I'll make her ſure:</p>
                  <p>Truſt not a woman, they have found the herb</p>
                  <p>To open locks, not braſen towers can hold 'em:</p>
                  <p>Or if they get not looſe, they have the vertue</p>
                  <p>Of Load-ſtones ſhut up in a box; they'll draw</p>
                  <p>Cuſtomers to 'em; nay being dead and buryed,</p>
                  <p>There is ſuſpition they will break the grave;</p>
                  <p>Which puts ſo many husbands to the charge</p>
                  <p>Of heavie ſtones, to keep their bad wives under.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Juſt.</speaker>
                  <p>You are mov'd.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh Maſter Juſtice, you are honeſt:</p>
                  <p>I have been abus'd, ſo miſerable cheated,</p>
                  <p>I am aſham'd to think on't: ſtay, what Muſick?—</p>
                  <stage>Muſick.</stage>
                  <p>Ha! 'tis my Neece; the very, very ſame.</p>
                  <stage>Enter Lambert and Neece.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                  <p>There, ſir, you have her, and the reſt is mine.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Take it—And you ſhall go along with me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neece.</speaker>
                  <p>How, Unkle!</p>
                  <p>A reveller? you'll lead me a Coranto.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>You ſhall dance homewards.</p>
                  <stage>Enter Playfair and his Brother.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>What make you ſo familiar with my wife?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Ha! wife! is ſhe married?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bro.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis upon record,</p>
                  <p>I'll bring a Parſon that ſhall take his oath on't.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Give me my bond and mony, Maſter Juſtice:</p>
                  <p>Where? where?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                  <p>Here, but they are not to be recover'd</p>
                  <p>By law: I have a judgement, ſir, againſt you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>You have conſpir'd, to rob, cheat and undo me:</p>
                  <p>You ſhall be all Star-Chamber'd.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neece.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, be calm, and hear us.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>I'll hear nothing.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, you ſhall,</p>
                  <p>It will be neceſſary: I am bold,</p>
                  <p>Perſuming on her favour to demand</p>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:35542:32"/>
                  <p>A parcel of three thouſand pound; the ſum</p>
                  <p>Belongs to me by vertue of a marriage,</p>
                  <p>And I muſt have it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Vertue of a marriage?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Juſt.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſaw the Prieſt conjoyn their hands; he will</p>
                  <p>Deſerve your love.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                  <p>Perhaps you may continue</p>
                  <p>A thouſand, or two thouſand on ſecurity.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>What perſecution this?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bro.</speaker>
                  <p>Faith ſir conſider,</p>
                  <p>'Tis more ſafe to ſee her thus beſtowed,</p>
                  <p>Then truſt a Jury; if the Doctor had</p>
                  <p>Given her too much Opium, or purg'd</p>
                  <p>Her ſoul away, things might go worſe: but I'll</p>
                  <p>Keep counſel.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>So, ſo, have ye mortified me yet?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                  <p>For your own ſake, and as you are a true knight,</p>
                  <p>I'll tell no tales.</p>
                  <stage>Enter Miſtreſs Bellamy, Frances, Hartwel and Cloſe.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Now have ye done?—The widow,</p>
                  <p>Not a word more: take her, I'll pay you, ſir,</p>
                  <p>Three thouſand pound to morrow: Noble widow,</p>
                  <p>You were in the firſt liſt to be invited;</p>
                  <p>My Neece I told you of, is married to</p>
                  <p>This worthy Gentleman.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>You look like a bridegroom.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis in your power to make it good, what ſay you?</p>
                  <p>Shall we joyn iſſue?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bel.</speaker>
                  <p>I will never matry.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>You are reſolv'd, why ſo? come hither Nephew,</p>
                  <p>Sha't be my heir, I love thee for thy wit;</p>
                  <p>But charm thy friends, they do not laugh at me:</p>
                  <p>I'll be a knight too, if I live, and build</p>
                  <p>An Hoſpital for twenty more o'th' Order;</p>
                  <p>Which I'll reduce my ſelf, out of the Suburbs,</p>
                  <p>In women's petticoats, and turn Squires again</p>
                  <p>To Whores, or Paraſites to Noblemen,</p>
                  <p>For want of fit proviſion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play</speaker>
                  <p>An excellent</p>
                  <p>Foundation: but where's <hi>Startup?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                  <p>Sunk, I think.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>Ne'er conjure for him: we are ingrateful to</p>
                  <p>Our bliſs, for waſting of theſe pretious minutes,</p>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:35542:32"/>
                  <p>Which are ſo many ages, till the Church</p>
                  <p>Hath made us perfect.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hor.</speaker>
                  <p>Is there any more work</p>
                  <p>For the Prieſt? then give you joy beforehand,</p>
                  <p>And let us celebrate the day together.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cloſe.</speaker>
                  <p>I am glad of your converſion, y'are the firſt</p>
                  <p>Jew, that in my remembrance has turn'd Chriſtian.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Play.</speaker>
                  <p>Walk on to joyes;</p>
                  <p>Twixt Love and Fortune, now th' accompts are even.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hart.</speaker>
                  <p>A chain of Hearts, and the firſt linck in Heaven.</p>
                  <stage>Exeunt omnes</stage>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="epilogue">
               <head>EPILOGUE.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THrough many hazards, Love hath found a way</l>
                  <l>For Friends to meet: good Omen to our Play.</l>
                  <l>If love hath brought you hither, Gentlemen,</l>
                  <l>Love will find out the way to come agen.</l>
                  <l>And we dare promiſe, if you relliſh theſe,</l>
                  <l>Our Loves ſhall find out other ways to pleaſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>T. B.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <p>There is lately Printed two excellent Comedies, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, <hi>The Old Couple:</hi> By <hi>Thomas May</hi> Eſquire.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The City-Night-Cap,</hi> or <hi>Crede quod habes &amp; habes.</hi> By <hi>Robert Davenport.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Both theſe, with variety of other Playes, are to be ſold by <hi>Samuel Speed,</hi> at the Printing Preſs in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-Yard. 1661.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
